........
........
Now, let us host the next broadcast, Ms. Wang Fan Sheng vice director
Now, let us host the next broadcast, Ms. Wang Fan Sheng vice director
Please give him a round of applause
Please give him a round of applause
Welcome Professor Qu and fellow individuals
Welcome Professor Qu and fellow individuals
Our knowledge feast is a very important event for our hospital to promote popular science facts
我們的知識饗宴是一個本院推廣科普事實非常重要的活動
Every month we invite lifted scholars from inside and outside the academy
每個月我們都邀請院內外解除了學者
Experts come here to talk about the latest academic developments
專家來這裡跟大家談最新的學術發展
Today, there are 1.3 or 1.4 times in each month here are humanities and social sciences
今天在這每個月這裡面有1.3就是1.4次是人文跟社會科學
It's all hosted by me in the Humanities and Social Sciences Association
都是由我來主持人文跟社會科學會會會主持
Today we are very honored to invite Professor Xu Wanwen from the Humanities and Social Sciences Research Center of our school to give a speech
今天我們非常榮幸能請到本院人文社會科學研究中心的徐萬文教授來演講
Professor Xu Wanwen is a graduate of the Department of Economics, National Taiwan University
徐萬文教授是台大經濟系畢業
After graduation, he went to Stanford University in the United States to obtain a Ph.D. in Finance
在畢業之後到美國史丹佛大學獲得金融學博士
Once taught at the University of Notre Dame and the University of California, Los Angeles
曾經在美國的聖母大學跟加州大學洛杉磯分校認教
He also served as the deputy counseling secretary of the academic counseling association of the college
也曾經擔任本院的學術諮詢總會副諮詢祕書
And there is a fertility support to see me
並且是有一份生育卓助的看我
Editor-in-Chief and Deputy Consultant of Taiwan Social Research Institute
台灣社會研究機關的主編跟副諮詢
Professor Xu is also in the Economics Department of National Taiwan University
徐教授同時也在台灣大學經濟系
National Taiwan University Physiognomy Institute
台大生相所
Chuo University's Industrial Economics Institute
中央大學的產經所
part-time professor
兼任教授
Professor Xu's research seems to me
徐教授的研究在我看起來
There is one point worth pointing out again.
有一點特別值得要再提出來
Just when everyone is being very small
就是在大家都被非常小的問題
when limited in here
局限在這裡面的時候
It's a minority that takes a lot of weight
它是少數還非常重視
Overall Industrial Economic Policy
整體的產業經濟政策
Scholars with Industrial Economic Development
跟產業經濟發展的學者
so its writings
所以它的著作
including many
包括有好多部
Among them, the following public language matters
其中下這個公語事之間
Alternative Thoughts on Taiwan's Economic Development
台灣經濟發展的另類思考
Taiwan's economy under globalization
全球化下的台灣經濟
Mechanisms of economic growth, etc.
經濟成長的機制等等
in 2003
在2003年
it collaborates with an american scholar
它與一位美國學者合作
A special book on the study of Taiwan's industrial upgrading
談台灣產業升級的研究的一部專書
Published immediately from the public circle in the United States
在美國馬上離公圈出版
There are many other works
還有好多部著作
These works are all about the upgrading of the industry
這些著作都是在研究產業的升級
Post-war economic development and other related issues
戰後的經濟發展等等相關的問題
In recent years, Professor Qi has also begun to conduct
近年來齊教授也開始進行
Research on China's economic development model after the reform and opening up
有關中國改革開放之後的經濟發展模式的研究
he is in this
他是在這方面
When I talked about the economic development of East Asia and other areas
在我談到了東亞經濟發展等領域
All Fertility Scholars
所有生育的學者
Today he is coming to share with you a speech
今天他要來跟大家分享的一個演講
After the inheritance of the Republic of China
是民國傳承以後
The Inheritance of the Republic of China and the Post-war Economic Development of Taiwan
民國傳承以台灣戰後經濟發展
I think we have a lot to look forward to today's speech
我想我們對今天的演講有許多期待
We now welcome Professor Qi with warm applause
我們現在就以熱烈掌聲歡迎齊教授
Thank you Dean of Protection
謝謝防護院長
Thank you so much for listening to me so late
非常謝謝大家來聽我這麼晚了
come hear me say something
來聽我說一些
my research results
我的研究成果
The topic I want to talk about today is the inheritance of the Republic of China and Taiwan's post-war economic development
我今天要講的題目是民國傳承與台灣戰後經濟發展
Let me first explain why I want to talk about this topic
我先解釋一下我為什麼要講這個題目
This is of course related to my recent research
這當然跟我最近的研究有關
After I returned to Taiwan more than 20 years ago
就是我20多年前回到台灣之後
Let me start first, as Wang Fu just mentioned
我先開始就像剛王富提到的
I study Taiwan
我研究台灣
Comparing recent economic development in the last 30 years
比較近期的後30年經濟發展
especially
尤其是
Shangde Instrument is the industrial upgrading of Taiwan's high-tech industry in the past 20 years
上德文書是台灣高科技業這20年的產業升級
But the more I research, the more I feel that we
但是我越研究越覺得說我們
It seems that Taiwan's economy has arrived
好像台灣經濟到了
The recent transformation
最近這個轉型
is in a bind
是陷入一個困局
That's the dilemma with its big background
那是困局有它很大的背景
So I gradually started to watch
所以我漸漸就開始去看
Taiwan
台灣
just want to ask
就想要問
The further issue is Taiwan's post-war economic development
更遠的問題就是說台灣戰後經濟發展
how did it start
怎麼開始的
The more I research, the more interesting and complicated this problem seems to be.
我愈來愈研究就發現這個問題好像更有趣 更複雜
So I became like half a historian
所以我就變成好像也半個歷史學家
Maybe historians don't agree
或許歷史學者不承認
But at least I also started to publish an article in Taiwan History Research
但是至少我也開始在台灣史研究去登了一篇文章
Also published an article in New Historiography
在新史學也登了一篇文章
even if the field isn't very... how to say
就即使這個領域不是很...怎麼講
not taken seriously
不是很被重視
But more and more I feel like looking at these things from a historical perspective
但是我愈來愈覺得用歷史的角度去看這些事情
is very important and very rewarding
是非常重要並且非常有收穫
At the same time, I found it difficult to say things at the beginning.
同時我發現說事情都是開頭難
That's me
就是我譬如說我研究這二十幾年來
The industrial upgrading of Taiwan's high-tech industry is not easy
台灣高科技業的產業升級也不容易
But it is in the past sixty years
但是它是在過去這六十年來
Especially what can only happen on the basis of electricity in the past thirty years
尤其是前三十年所電力的基礎下才能發生的事
So I went back and studied the first thirty years
所以我就回去研究前三十年
From 1945, 1949
從1945、1949開始
especially
尤其是
So I've been focusing on the 1950s lately
所以我最近是聚焦在1950年代
Taiwan's post-war economic development
到底臺灣的戰後的經濟發展
how did it start
是怎麼開始的
So this is what I've been doing for about ten years
所以這是我大概這十年來
a focused study
一個重點的研究
then my research today
那我今天的研究
In particular it will be
會特別談到的是
how to explain
怎麼樣去解釋
Taiwan's postwar economic development
臺灣戰後的經濟發展
this motive
這個動機
quite complicated
比較複雜
that's what i found out
就是我發現說
In the process of democratization in Taiwan
臺灣在這個民主化過程中
how to explain
對於怎麼樣解釋
Taiwan's Postwar Economic Development
臺灣的戰後經濟發展
In fact, there is a mainstream argument
其實是有一個主流的論述
there for
那裡面對於
Legacy of Japanese Colonization
日本殖民的遺產
special affirmation
特別的肯定
Also highly affirmed the role of the United States
對於美國的角色也高度的肯定
It is also highly negative for the national government
對於國民政府也是高度的否定
I'm a little confused about this situation
我就對於這個情況有一點困惑
I also feel
同時我也覺得
Backward countries all over the world must go through a process of decolonization
全世界的落後國家都必須要經過一個去殖民化的過程
That is to say, backward countries were more or less former colonies
就是說落後國家多多少少都曾經是殖民地
then how do you develop your own economy
那你怎麼樣去發展自己的經濟
How to face your colonial experience in this process
在這過程中怎麼樣去面對自己殖民的經驗
is a serious challenge
是一個很嚴重的挑戰
I'm disturbed by how much I think about the present
我對於目前很多的看法讓我不安
For example, to give a very simple example
譬如說舉一個很簡單的例子
this May
今年五月的時候
In order to commemorate the designer of the Jianan Army
在為了紀念嘉南大軍的設計者
Batian language also see
巴田語亦見了
his memorial park
他的紀念園區
into his memorial
進了他的紀念館
President Ma also attended in person
馬總統也親自出席
The whole discourse is very grateful to him
整個論述是對他非常地感恩
then i was thinking
那我在想說
then we know
那我們知道
What reservoir and who built it?
什麼水庫是誰建的嗎
we for
我們對於
Who built such a reservoir?
這麼水庫誰建的嗎
do we know
我們知道嗎
are we grateful
我們有感恩嗎
Is there any criticism?
有批評嗎
so
所以
This makes me feel like saying
這樣子讓我覺得說
haven't we done it yet
我們是不是還沒有做到
be humble
能夠以不卑不亢的態度
to review
去檢討
to confront past colonial experience
去面對過去的殖民經驗
this is not just
這個並不只是
that's all
這樣子而已
Because what I'm trying to say here is to say
因為我要想在這裡說的就是說
This is the same as our current
這個跟我們目前的
Economic and political difficulties are related
經濟政治的困局有關係
then i hope
那我希望
after i speak
我講了之後
can convince everyone
可以說服大家
maybe it has something to do with it
或許是有點關係
I guess part of this dilemma
我想這個困局的部分
I think you don't need me to say more
我想大家好像不用我來多說
everyone will agree
大家都會同意
That is to say, it is a political dilemma
就是說目前是一個政治上的困局
not what i want to say
不是我要說
But with the political dilemma
但是但隨著政治的困局
We also have our economic difficulties
我們也有我們經濟的困局
We lack economic vision
我們缺乏經濟的願景
We also lack how to go
我們也缺乏怎麼樣去
pursuing economic vision
追求經濟願景的
economic policy
經濟政策
At the same time I don't know if you have noticed
同時我不知道大家有沒有注意到
we don't talk much these days
我們近來很少談
a concept called economic vision
一個概念叫做經濟願景
no one talks
沒有人談
This is of course a very dangerous thing
這當然是一個很危險的事情
I call this an economic dilemma
我把這個叫做經濟上的一個困局
What I'm going to say today is to say
我今天要來講的就是說
why are we like this
為什麼我們現在是這個樣子
I certainly wish to say that if I
我當然希望說如果我今天
My research is hoping to clarify this issue
我的研究是希望能夠釐清這個議題
then help us to be able to
然後幫助我們能夠
then go
然後再出發
ok, let me talk about it first
好,那我先講一下
that is
就是
Taiwanese society
台灣社會
Of course we are in Taiwan
我們台灣當然是
have a lot of grades
有很多的成績
for a while
在有一陣子
we'll be called say
我們會被稱為說
we have double miracle
我們有雙奇蹟
our economy is a miracle
我們的經濟是奇蹟
then for a while
然後陣子
we are very gentle
我們以非常溫和
means of peace
和平的手段
achieved democratization
達到了民主化
Also considered a miracle of democracy
也被認為是民主奇蹟
So we say it's
所以我們說這是
Tin-Lirical Double Miracle
Tin-Lirical雙重的奇蹟
very proud achievement
非常傲人的成績
but everything
但是所有事情
seems to have its price
好像都有它的代價
then we are
那我們在
i'm here to say
我要在這裡說
as we democratize
就我們在民主化之後
our society
我們社會
a mainstream discourse
形成了一種主流的論述
mainstream discourse
這個主流的論述
very powerful
非常的有力
it goes deep
它深入人心
but it doesn't
但是它沒有
We ask which scholar
我們問說哪一個學者
Did this write a book?
這個寫了書沒有
Which scholar has established a scholarly basis for this without
哪一位學者為這個建立了學術的基礎沒有
but but everyone knows
但是 但是大家都知道
it's baby talk
是這以兒語的方式
Can't bear it
管不忍心
good
好
Okay, let me briefly talk about the economic part
好 我簡單講一下就經濟的部分
The prevailing discourse goes like this
這個主流的論述是這樣說的
is how to explain Taiwan's economic miracle
就是如何解釋台灣經濟的奇蹟
Because that part should be undeniable anyway
因為無論如何那個部分應該是無法否定的
that would say
那就會說
It should be the credit of Japanese colonial rule
應該是日本殖民統治的功勞
or american role
或者是美國的角色
If you don't want to be sure about this
如果這個都不願意肯定的話
That means the people work very hard
那就是說人民非常的努力
The most important part is the negative part
最重要的是否定的這個部分
It is to deny the contribution of the Kuomintang and the National Government
就是要否定說國民黨國民政府的功勞
Although it is said that economic development should be the responsibility of the national government
雖然說經濟發展應該是國民政府
The best piece in the first year after the war
在戰後最起始年來成績最好的一塊
All other parts are subject to these discounts
其他的部分都要打這些折扣
This argument holds that the Kuomintang, for its own benefit,
這個論述認為國民黨為了一己之施
Established a monopoly party-state capital
建立了壟斷性的黨國資本
Obstructing the private sector is of no use to Taiwan
阻礙民營無功於台灣
So it emphasizes the opposition to party-state authoritarianism
所以它強調的是反對黨國威權
emphasis on nativism
強調本土主義
Then with this support is
然後跟這個支持的是
The neoliberalism of our economics
我們經濟學的新自由主義
Compared with mainstream discourses in Taiwanese society
相對於台灣社會的主流論述
Blue Camp is basically
藍營基本上是
no words no discussion
無言沒有論述
ok then let's take a look
好 那我們先來看一下
this
這個
Taiwan economy
台灣經濟
Development achievements
發展的成績
From the perspective of the world
在世界的角度來看
how
是如何
ok this is
好 這個是
Medicine
Medicine
experts in this field
研究這方面的專家
he is very powerful
他很厲害 他把
all countries in the world
全球所有國家
this thousand years
這個一千年來
a thousand years
一千年來的
All GDP counted
所有的GDP都算了
So my reliability
所以我這個可靠度
Nobody knows
沒有人知道
But it's our only basis
但是是我們唯一的根據
In recent decades
這近幾十年
Of course, the World Bank and the IMF
當然這個世界銀行跟IMF
have some estimates
有一些估計
But you said this hundred years
但是你說這一百年
We can only see him for a thousand years
一千年我們只有看他的
ok let's see
好 我們看一下
Postwar 1950 to 1998
戰後1950到1998
he provided us
他給我們提供的
Global We Divide Western Europe
全球我們分西歐
United States Latin America Eastern Europe All Soviet Union
美國 拉丁 美洲 東歐 全蘇聯
Africa East Asia
非洲 東亞
1950 1998
1950年1998年
their real per capita income
他們的實質人均所得
let's take a look
我們看一下
Taiwan in 1950 was 936 yuan
台灣在1950年是936元
It was a certain one in 1990
就是1990年某一個
Let's count it in dollars.
算美元的計價單位吧
We saw
我們看到
one tenth
十分之一
By 1998
到了1998年
It is about 55% of the United States
是美國的55%左右
We can see that
我們可以看到
I'm going to show you the Philippines
我要讓大家看一下的是菲律賓
in 1950
在1950年的時候
The Philippines was a role model for Taiwan at that time
菲律賓那個時候是台灣的榜樣
just younger friends
就是年輕一點的朋友
probably unbelievable
大概難以相信
but at that time
但是那個時候
The per capita income of the Philippines is higher than that of Taiwan
菲律賓的人均所得是高於台灣的
And everyone thinks that the Philippines
並且大家都覺得菲律賓
that time
那個時候
If we look at the remarks at that time
如果我們去看那個時候的言論的話
Everyone thinks that the Philippines is more advanced
都會覺得菲律賓是比較超前的
Everyone remembers he was an American colony
大家記得他是美國的殖民地
But in this nearly 50 years
但是在這個將近50年
in that time
那時間裡面
The Philippines has only grown
菲律賓只成長了
only doubled
只翻了一倍
But Taiwan's per capita income has increased by 16 times
但是台灣的人均所得翻了16倍
let's take a look at that
讓我們看一下就是說
economic development
經濟發展
So economic development is a
所以經濟發展是一個
how to say
怎麼講
a catching up process
一個追趕的過程
In other words, you take the developing countries of Western Europe, America and Japan as a goal to catch up with them
也就是說你是以西歐美日的發展國家當作一個目標去追趕它
So if you look at Western Europe and the United States, they are very mature
所以你看一下西歐美國他們已經很成熟了
So the multiple of their growth is more than three times
所以他們成長的倍數就三倍多左右
Latin America's development is ahead of ours
拉丁美洲它的發展比我們超前
But its development is also quite
但是它的發展也相當
Not developing well during this time
在這段時間發展並不好
It only grew 2.3 times
它只有成長了2.3倍
Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union are backward
東歐蘇聯是落後
Africa is also behind
非洲也是落後
Therefore, the countries in East Asia can be said to be an exception in the backward countries
所以東亞的國家在落後國家可以說是一個例外
That is, the speed of growth far exceeds the goal we want to catch up with.
就是成長的速度遠超過我們要追趕的目標
Therefore, we have successfully shortened the distance between us and the target we want to catch up with.
因此成功的縮短了我們跟我們要追趕目標的距離
Among the backward countries, very few
在落後國家中間是極少數在過
In the next 50 to 60 years, there are very few backward countries that have achieved this goal
在後這五六十年中極少數達到這個目標的落後國家
so
所以
let's look again
我們再來看一下
Because the one just now was in 1998
因為剛剛那個是到1998年
And then if we look at 2010 it's
然後如果我們來看一下2010年就是
The latest information we can have
我們能夠有的最新的資料
Ranking of real GDP per capita of countries based on IMF
就IMF算的各國實質人均GDP的排名
According to Purchasing Power Parity
就是按照Purchasing Power Parity
deflating purchasing power
就是購買力平減
good
好
We can see that Taiwan ranks 21
我們可以看到台灣排名21
Then this value is very high
然後這個數值是很高的
More than 35,000 US dollars
35,000多美金
This is a bit of a favor
這個有點受寵獲金
But I guess this is showing that
不過我想這個是顯示說
In fact, we are very used to
其實我們非常習慣了
Our prices in Taiwan
我們台灣的物價
Very stable for decades
這幾十年來非常的穩定
so everyone see
所以大家看
this japanese korean
這個日本韓國
Japan we always feel that he should
日本我們總覺得他應該
His Life Scholar should be higher than ours
他生活學者應該比我們高吧
But maybe it's because he's too expensive
但或許是因為他物價太高
so he flattened out
所以他平減下來
still behind Taiwan
還排在台灣後面
so this is
所以這個是
If we remove the first 20 middle
如果我們去掉前面20個中間
remove the words of several petro-states
去掉幾個石油國家的話
Taiwan should be
台灣應該是
Ranked 17th
排名第17
ok so this is a
好,所以這是一個
very remarkable achievement
非常了不起的成就
Then this development
然後這個發展
is also quite average
也是相當的平均
is stable
就是是平穩的
continuous
持續的
Let's take a look at some important
容看一下一些重要的
Economic Indicators
經濟指標
Real GDP
實質 GDP
the first 30 years
前30年
nearly 10% faster
將近10%的速度
growing up
成長
So now everyone feels
所以現在大家都覺得
Mainland China is amazing
中國大陸不得了
10% per year
每年10%
In fact, Taiwan was almost like this in the first 30 years
其實台灣前30年也差不多是這樣子
no better than them
並不比他們
That is to say, it is developing surprisingly
也就是在發展出奇
all at such a fast pace
都是以這麼快的速度
growing up
成長
We're looking at him because of the slowing population growth
這個我們看他因為人口的成長減緩
so later
所以到後來
This growth slows down
這個雖然成長也減緩
But our per capita GDP is still growing
但我們人均GDP還在成長
OK, let's take a look at the price index at the end.
好 那最後我們看一下這個物價指數
that's what i just said
就是我剛剛講的就是這個
Because of the national government's fear of quitting
因為國民政府的戒勝恐懼
So the price stability is
所以這個物價的穩定是
is a policy objective that they successfully achieved
是他們成功達成的一個政策目標
that's what i think
那也是我覺得
just why
就剛才為什麼
Why this real per capita GDP can rank among the best
為什麼這個實質的人均GDP可以排名列前茅
It is also because our price level is quite stable
也是因為我們物價的水準相當的穩定
Okay, so this is the achievement of our economic development
好 所以這個是我們經濟發展的成績
That shouldn't be too much of a doubt
那應該是沒有什麼太大的疑問
an economic miracle
可以說是一個經濟的奇蹟
Of course I won't say the other part
當然另外一部分我不說
That is to say, in the first thirty years
就是說在前三十年的話
The achievement of this economic development is also
這個經濟發展的成績也是
but with fairly average
但隨著相當平均
and more average
並且更加平均的
status of distribution
所得分配的狀態
good
好
Let me talk about my structure first
我先講一下我的架構
that is
就是
How does the country develop economy
路互國家如何發展經濟
Let's look at East Asia as a
我們看一下東亞是一個
few exceptions
例外少數的
what conditions are needed
需要什麼樣的條件
We know that the road mutual countries have to learn
我們知道路互國家必須要學習
Western advanced production methods
西方先進的生產方式
their productivity
他們的生產力
their technology
他們的技術
how they are organized
他們的組織方式
their business management
他們的企業管理
we all have to learn
我們都要學習
But it's important to say
但是很重要的一點就是說
Although we have to learn
我們雖然要學習
But we have to learn by ourselves
但是是我們自己要學習
That is to say, we need to have our own space
也就是說我們需要有自主的空間
to develop your abilities
來發展自己的能力
grow our democratic industries
發展我們民主的產業
democratic business
民主的企業
at this initial stage
在這個起始的階段
we need to get together
我們需要去抵聚
We need to resist this external force
我們需要去抗拒這個外來的力量
because especially when you start
因為尤其在你開始的時候
Your strength is so far apart
你的力量是相差的那麼遠
That is to say, for example, during the Japanese occupation
也就是說譬如說在日據時期
Why Taiwan's local power
為什麼臺灣本地的力量
The power of industry developed so little
工業的力量發展得那麼少
It was also because of the advanced power of Japan at that time
也是因為那個時候跟日本先進的力量
is so far away
是距離那麼遠
Then you don't get policy support
然後你得不到政策的支持
But it's important to say
但是很重要的就是說
You must have such a motivation
你必須要有這樣的一個動力
a wish
一個意願
You have to make a vow that I will do this thing
你要發願說我要做這件事情
you need to be motivated
你需要有這樣的動力
the will of such will
這樣的意願的意志
I call this the will to develop
我把這個叫做發展的意志
The Will to Develop
The Will to Develop
We in social science tend to think of ourselves
我們社會科學比較想要把自己
become a science
變成一個科學
So don't talk about this
所以不太談這種這種
this element of subjectivity
主觀性的這種因素
but what i want to say
但是我要說的
it exists
它存在
Then we social sciences can't
然後我們社會科學也不能
Truly claiming that we are science
真正號稱我們是科學
We are between science and
我們是介於科學跟
Between Science and Art
這個Science and Art之間的
that number
那這個號
the other two conditions
那另外兩個條件
is the ability to drive development
是推動發展的能力
This is it
就是這個
is that you must be able to
就是你必須要有能力去
go wrong about these things
去錯對這些事情
yes there
有有
The economy is dead
經濟無機了
can you handle it
你是不是可以處理
let us pass safely
讓我們可以平安過關
it takes ability
這是需要能力的
that in addition
那另外
need some external conditions
需要一些外在的條件
what i want to say is
那我要說的是
In the early postwar period in Taiwan
在台灣戰後初期
inherited by the national government
國民政府繼承的
The old kings of the Chinese nation survived in vain
中華民族舊王徒存的
Chinese nationalism
中華民族主義
since the Opium War
就是從鴉片戰爭以降
so
這樣
Developed over a hundred years
一百多年發展出來的
Chinese nationalism
中華民族主義
plus
加上
National Government
國民政府
Production and loan experience
產貸的經驗
They brought their will to develop to Taiwan
他們到台灣帶來了他們發展的意志
I'll wait for him to talk
我等他也會講說
what is the external condition
這個外在的條件是什麼
So this is the architecture I explained
所以這個是我解釋的架構
So the following I will order
所以以下我將要順序
Discuss these in order
依順序討論這些
I Japan's Colonial Influence on America's Role
我日本殖民統治的影響美國的角色
The actions of the national government and its will to develop
國民政府的作為跟他發展的意志
Then I'll discuss the role of financial bureaucrats
然後我要討論財經官僚的角色
Then I have to give them a name
那我也要給他們取個名字
Ruguan, who is called saving the country by industry, takes Ying Zhongrong as an example
叫做實業救國的如官以營中容為案例
Finally, let me discuss the development of the main body capacity and transformation of the new country.
然後最後我來討論一下發展新國這樣的主體能力跟轉型
So this is my content for today
所以這是我今天的這個內容
Okay, so let's talk about Japan's role first.
好 那我們先討論日本的角色
Ok this one, I should all agree that Japan has done a lot of things in Taiwan
好 這個 我應該都會同意日本在台灣做了很多事情
Zhangliang land lays the foundation for modernization
丈良土地 奠立了現代化的基礎
It not only paves the way, but also introduces and establishes a modern system
不只是照橋鋪路 並且也引入了 建立了現代化的制度
with the organization
跟組織
But he mainly puts this part in a global perspective first
不過他主要是首先這個部分要把它擺在一個全球的視野
That is to say, the imperialists and colonists have arrived in the colonies
就是說帝國主義者 殖民者到了殖民地
most of them do these things more or less
大多數多多少少有做這些事情
I once read an article where he compares different colonies
我曾經看過一篇文章 他比較 就是比較不同殖民地
he has various indicators
他有各種指標
This is electricity, roads, what is the cost
就是這個電力 道路 什麼視資率
What a bunch of indicators for universal education
教育普及利亞什麼一堆指標
Japan's colonies did not rank high on all indicators
日本的殖民地並沒有在所有的指標都名列前茅
I remember that it is probably ranked first in Taiwan Electric Power
我記得大概在電力台灣是排第一
but generally good
但是大致還不錯
But it's not just Japanese imperialism doing this
但是並不是只有日本帝國主義做這個事情
Of course, the author thinks that the UK is also doing a good job.
當然那個作者是覺得英國也做得不錯
he is an englishman
他是一個英國人
But he did collect those metrics for us
但是他確實幫我們收集了那些指標
Then there is a display saying
然後有顯示說
Indeed, in order to carry out his colonial enterprise in the colony, the colonist
確實殖民者為了要在殖民地進行他的殖民事業
he has to do these things too
他也必須做這些事情
Well, so is Japan
好 那日本也是這樣
He is in the colony of Taiwan
他在台灣這個殖民地
He mainly wants to turn Taiwan into a supplier of Mi Tang to Japan
他主要是要把台灣變成米唐的供應地 供應日本
But he thus helped establish a modern agriculture in Taiwan
但他因此在台灣幫助建立了現代化的農業
and then indeed successfully
然後確實成功地
Make Taiwan a base for supplying Mitang to Japan
讓台灣成為供給米塘到日本的基地
What we want to see is modernization and the establishment of modern industry
我們要看的是現代化以及現代工業的建立
in previous decades
在前幾十年
The modern industry established by Japan is mainly to control sugar
日本所建立的現代工業主要是治糖
by the time the war started
到了戰爭開始了
It did some military industrialization in Taiwan
它在台灣做了一些軍需工業化
but
但是
According to scholars I respect
依據我很尊敬的學者
Soil feast
土教宴
he thinks that
他是認為說
because
因為
Because Japan did not waver in Taiwan
因為日本在台灣並沒有去動搖
The most fundamental structure of the landlord economy
最根本地主經濟的架構
Then modern industries are all Japanese-funded
然後現代工業都是日資
so he thinks
所以他認為
He thinks Taiwan is not capitalized
他認為台灣沒有資本主義化
Industrialization started after the war
工業化是戰後啟動
Because modern industry is an enclave transplanted by Japan
因為現代工業是日本移植的飛地
The capital, technology and management personnel of modern industry are all Japanese
現代工業的資本 技術 管理人才都是日本人
And the Japanese education system is also compatible with this arrangement
並且日本的教育制度也與這樣子的安排是相配合的
doesn't train natives to do things like this
並不訓練本地人去做這樣的事情
Therefore, the colonial government organization and the Japanese and Chinese natives occupied
因此殖民政府組織跟日之中本地人所佔領
Occupies a relatively lower position
所佔據的是比較下層的位置
When it was accepted in 1945, people from the province who were appointed or above by the Japanese colonial government
1945年接收的時候 日本殖民政府中委任以上的本省人
only 2.2%
只佔2.2%
The most famous is Zhu Congming's 11 professors
最有名就是朱聰明11位教授
But of course the important thing is this
但當然很重要的就是這個
temporary mobilization system
暫時動員體系
Is a
是一個
is a totalitarian
是一個屬度極權的
system of domination
統治的體系
Because we know that the Japanese are temporarily
因為我們知道就是說日本人在暫時
he gradually
他逐步的
further deprived the landowners of their power
進一步剝奪了地主的力量
So it is a highly mobilized system for war
所以是一個高度為了戰爭動員的體系
So he left a lot of room
因此他留下了很大的空間
Let the national government take over
讓國民政府來接收
But Taiwan is lucky
但是台灣有幸運之處
Japan's colonists are defeated colonists
日本他這個殖民者是戰敗的殖民者
so he must evacuate completely
因此他必須完全撤離
is his advanced economic power
就是他的先進的經濟力量
Including capital technology management talents
包括資本技術管理人才
You could say he created a vacuum of talent at the top
你可以說他造成了上層的人才的真空狀態
But the entire advanced Japanese-owned enterprise
但是整個先進的日資企業
Advanced forces are also fully withdrawn
先進的力量也完全撤出
unlike in colonial times he was dominant
不像在殖民時期他是主導
In the colonial period it was not only... I think it can be divided into two factors
在殖民時期不單是...我想可以分成兩個因素
One is that Japanese companies are of course more advanced
一個就是說日本企業當然他比較先進
The other is that the policy also highly restricts the development of local modern enterprises, at least in the early days.
另外一個就是政策上也至少在早期是高度限制本地人現代企業的發展
Okay, so Taiwan is lucky in this respect that other backward regions do not have
好 所以台灣在這一點上是有一個其他落後地區沒有的幸運
the colonists are gone
就是殖民者走了
We know many other colonists such as France who was defeated by Japan and kicked out of Vietnam
我們知道很多其他的殖民者譬如說法國他被日本打敗了趕出越南
In the end, he actually said that he would return to Vietnam after four or five years.
結果他居然還後言的在四五年之後回到越南
Just reclam this place
就reclam這個地方
But so this is, for example, like Indonesia
那但是所以這個是譬如說像印尼
He still has to fight a war with this Dutchman who was kicked out by the Japanese and came back
他還要打一仗跟這個回來的被日本人趕掉的荷蘭人又回來了
The independence movement of Indonesia is going to drive the Dutch out again and again
印尼的這個獨立這個獨立運動者要去又去把荷蘭人趕掉
Just like Vietnam
就跟越南也是
Well so not even if politics won the Revolutionary War politically
好所以不即使政治在政治上贏得了獨立戰爭之後
This one for the colonists is not necessarily going to exit economically
殖民者的這個在經濟上未必會退出
Then Taiwan is our new master, the United States
那臺灣性我們的新新大主美國
Even the supporter behind the last one is also very tolerant
就是最後這個後面的這個支持者也特別的包容
For providing aid and also tolerating Taiwan's developmental state to promote industrialization
對於提供援助並且也容忍臺灣發展型國家推動工業化的作為
Then let me introduce a term called a developmental state
那我這裡介紹一個名詞叫做發展型國家
In our social sciences, it is called
那我們社會科學裡面叫做
development of state
development of state
refers to such a regime
就是指這樣的一個政權
its ruler
它的主政者
overall economic development
以整體經濟發展
priority target
為優先目標
development priority
發展優先
but very important
但是很重要的
is that it is based on
就是它是以
Overall development is a priority
整體的發展為優先
rather than individual vested interests
而不是個別的既得利益
I'll explain more later
那我等一下會再多做說明
ok that
好,那
Speaking of Japan
講到日本了
that this
那這個
look at america
來看一下美國
of course we know
我們當然知道
America after the war
美國在戰後
very very important to Taiwan
對台灣非常非常的重要
we see this year
我們看到今年
The two presidential candidates are still going
兩位總統候選人還要去
American Chamber of Commerce
美國商會
speak in english
以英文演講
we know this
我們就知道這個
The role of the United States is still very important
美國的角色還是非常的重要
good
好
Well
呃
Without the intervention of the United States
如果沒有美國的介入
if
如果
The Korean War didn't happen
韓戰沒有發生
america withdrew his support
美國撤出了他的支持
Maybe we are busy with reform and opening up right now
我們說不定現在正在忙著改革開放
so i tried this
所以我想這個
That is to say, the importance of the support of the United States
就是說美國的支持的重要性
I think there is no doubt
我覺得是無可置疑
After the Korean War
韓戰發生了之後
Military Aid Financial Aid Various
軍事援助 經濟援助各種
back again
又回來了
Of course in terms of financial aid
當然就經濟援助來講的話
To stabilize Taiwan's economy
對於穩定台灣的經濟
is very important
是非常重要
Because at that time inflation was
因為那個時候通貨膨脹是
tens of thousands
幾千幾萬的
But what I'm saying is
但是我要說的就是
We can't say these details
這些細節我們沒辦法說
but i want to point out that
但我要指出就是說
we are now
我們到現在
are rarely able to go
都很少能夠去
review
檢討
Review our dependence on the United States
檢討我們對美國的依賴
Review says Taiwan's dependence on US
檢討說台灣對美國的依賴
Influence on the United States on Taiwan
對美國對台灣的影響
That is a very big topic worthy of our discussion
那個是一個很很大很值得我們探討的議題
like when I was studying in America
像我在美國留學的時候
Taiwan is so small
台灣那麼小
more than 20 million people
兩千多萬人
Our overseas students who went to Taiwan are in the United States
我們台灣去的留學生在美國
belong to
都是屬於
It can't be said that it belongs to the number two, but also the number two and the number three.
不能說屬於數二也是數二數三吧
we can see this
我們可以看到這個
is disproportionately much
是不成比例的多
even now
即使到了現在
There is also mainland China ahead
前面也有了中國大陸
there is india
有印度
but
但是
Taiwan students
台灣留學生
Then we are also complaining
然後我們也在抱怨
Young Malays do not study abroad
馬來年輕人不留學
what? What
什麼什麼
so comfortable these
太舒服這些
but even so
但是即使這樣
Taiwan students
台灣的留學生
Still in the top five
在現在還是排到前五名的
I'm in Taiwan for international students in the United States
我就在美國國際留學生的台行裡面
still so many
還是這麼多
So if we go and see
所以如果我們去看看
once i did it
有一次我就做了
researching i found out that
研究我就發現說
latin america
拉丁美洲
They are so close to America
他們離美國那麼近
Do many of them choose America?
他們有很多人都選美國嗎
No
沒有
you say middle east africa
你說中東非洲
you look at the ratio
你去看這個比例
Ratio to population
跟人口的比例
far inferior to Taiwan
遠不如台灣
So our entire Taiwan
所以我們這個整個台灣
and East Asia to the United States
以及東亞對於美國
relationship with the United States
跟美國的關係
very reflective
就非常反映
our political dependence on him
我們在政治上對他的依賴
good
好
But what I'm saying is this
但我要說的這個是
That is to say, the role of the United States is very critical
就是說美國的角色非常地關鍵
but
但是
but we can't use dollars
但是我們不能夠用美元
to explain Taiwan's success
來解釋台灣的成功
because
因為
give two examples
舉兩個例子
First
第一
in the mainland period
就在大陸時期
United States to the National Government
美國對國民政府
That's the one
就是那個
The defeated America
兵敗如山倒的美國
And the national government
而國民政府
also provided more assistance
也曾經提供更多的援助
but no good results
但是並沒有很好的結果
Then everyone in the rest of the world
然後每人在世界其他地方
Also many most cases
也很多大多數情況
no good results
沒有很好的成效
so it's critical
所以它很關鍵
but can't explain
但不能解釋
But Taiwan is more fortunate
但台灣比較幸運的
that's what i just said
就是我剛講了
it has something to do with us
就是跟我們有關係的
one japan and one america
一個日本 一個美國
It gave Taiwan a postwar
它在戰後給了台灣一個
Economically relatively self-developed space
在經濟上相對自主開發的空間
This is of course an arrangement for the Cold War layout.
這個當然是冷戰布局的安排
So the United States provides an umbrella for Taiwan
所以美國對台灣提供保護傘
market
援助技術而跟市場
market is important
市場很重要
we are at
我們在
started in the 80s
在80年代開始
we'll hear 3011 or something
我們會聽到3011或什麼的
But the first 30 years
但是前30年
The United States is quite prosperous
美國是相當康海的
open its door
打開它的大門
Enter Taiwan's
輸入台灣的
Export
出口品
no apology like it started in the 80s
沒有像80年代開始那樣的道歉
At the same time, it is not in the market of Taiwan
同時它不介於台灣這個市場
too small to be far from it
太小了離它很遠
but at the same time it was for cold war political reasons
但同時它為了冷戰政治的原因
it tolerates the national government
它容忍國民政府
The industrialization of various developmental states
各種各樣發展型國家的工業化的作為
to protect the domestic market
就是保護國內市場
Supporting local industries and attracting foreign investment
扶植本地產業 抵聚外資
For example, all these actions are
譬如說 所有這些作為都是
America in the late 80s
美國在80年代後期
Start pushing the WTO
開始推WTO說
don't do this don't do this
不准做這個 不准做這些
It's from East Asia
就是原來東亞的
Four East Asian Tigers follow Japan's ICSID model
東亞四小龍追隨日本的通產審模式
Have you heard of the production review mode?
大家聽過通產審模式嗎
In fact, the Four East Asian Tigers are roughly
其實東亞四小龍大致就是
Following Japan's ICSID model
追隨日本的通產審模式
For example, foreign capital came
譬如說外資來了
just ask for it
就要求它
You have to train local suppliers
你要訓練本地的供應商
best for export
最好主要外銷
Are you constantly increasing the proportion of local purchases
你是不是不斷地提高本地購買比例
All of these are now banned by the WTO
所有這些到了現在的WTO都不准了
so of course it is
所以這當然是
Taiwan is actually
台灣在現實上
luckier in history
在歷史時刻是比較幸運的
Of course, it was also due to the arrangement of the Cold War.
當然也是因為冷戰的安排
This is the opposite of what the US does in Latin America
這個跟美國在拉丁美洲的做法相反
For example, we know that Chile elected Ayed
譬如說我們知道智利選出了阿葉德
Ayed is not just a leftist
阿葉德他不只是左派
And he's going to resist the influence of American corporations
並且他要去抗拒美國快要公司的勢力
He wants to nationalize the mines
他要把礦產國有化
Turns out we know he was overthrown in a coup and people were killed
結果我們知道他被政變推翻人也被殺
At the same time the United States
同時美國
after World War II
在二戰之後
In 1946, the Sino-US Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation was signed
1946年簽了中美友好通商航海條約
China fully opens its door to the United States
中國對美國全面開放門戶
and only for the US
並且只是單獨對美國
So it seems that the treaty seems to be still valid
所以好像據說這個條約好像還有效
I met a friend who works in the media
我碰到一個朋友做傳媒的
He said that now it seems that the movie imports something like this
他說現在好像電影進口什麼這些
still citing the treaty
還是在引用這個條約
i don't know
我就不知道了
I didn't check this part
我沒有去查這個部分
So what I'm saying is this is the paradox
所以我要說的這是吊詭之處
That is to say, it is the strategic consideration of the United States towards China.
就是說是美國對中國的戰略考量
Make it highly tolerant of Taiwan's economic autonomy
讓它對台灣的經濟自主高度的包容
Let's look at this more troublesome problem first.
我們先來看這個比較麻煩的問題
It is how we view the role of the national government
就是我們怎麼樣看待國民政府的角色
i mean to say
我想說就是說
We are in this process of democratization
我們在這個民主化的過程中
because we want
因為我們要
that our society does
就是我們社會確實
successful
成功的
relatively mild and peaceful approach
相對溫和 和平的方法
developed a discourse against authoritarian rule
發展出一套論述是反對威權統治的
This argument necessarily negates
這個論述必然會去否定
deny many parts of him
否定他的很多的部分
Variety
各種各樣
what i want to say is
我想要說的是
such a statement
這樣的論述
It's what I just said
就是我剛剛講的這樣的
Our current mainstream discourse
我們現在的主流論述
his staged tasks
他的階段性任務
should it come to an end
是不是應該告一段落
should we go
我們是不是應該去
to review the issue
去檢討這個問題
I guess I'm not saying this argument is completely useless
我想 我不是說這個論述完全沒有用
I'm not
從頭到尾都是 我不是
i feel everything
我是覺得所有的東西
Maybe we'll all have to look at it historically
可能我們都要歷史性地來看
For example, I just mentioned
譬如說我剛剛提到說
How do we view this mainstream discourse
我們怎麼樣看這個主流論述
How to see the impact of Japanese colonial rule
怎麼看日本殖民統治的影響
If you want to deny the authoritarian rule of the national government
如果你要去否定國民政府的威權統治
Of course it's easy for you to deny everything about him
你當然很容易就是否定他的一切
Then say the Japanese are doing better than you
然後就說日本人做得比你好
I just try to speak nice things about the Japanese
我就盡量說日本人的好話
then say bad things about you
然後來說你的壞話
you can imagine this
這個你可以想像說
This is an easy path
這個是一個很容易走的道路
but today
但是到了今天
Maybe we shouldn't take it so seriously
或許我們不應該要那麼信以為真
That way we'd better move on to the next step
這樣的話我們比較好走下一步
what i want to say is
我要說的是
In this mainstream discourse
這個主流論述裡面
will put the national government
會把國民政府
They just retreated and fled to Taiwan.
就是撤退 撤逃到台灣來的
said to be a
說成是一個
outright alien regime
徹底的外來政權
a colonial regime
一個殖民政權
It's very convenient to say this
這樣子的說法非常方便
it's easy
就是它很容易
it's just really embarrassing to say it
就是真的把它說得很不堪
easy to deny
很容易否定
but it has its price
但是它有它的代價
Saying this has its price
這樣說法有它的代價
then i'm coming
那我要來
that is
就是說
colonial power is not a
殖民政權不是一個
freely definable
隨便可以定義的
because it is a
因為它是一個
imperialist architecture
帝國主義的架構
that is, you have to have colonists
就是你要有殖民者
you have the colonized
你有被殖民者
at the same time
同時
This colonization is for the benefit of the mother country
這個殖民是為了母國的利益
and there should be differences in levels of development
並且應該有發展水平的差異
That is, the level of this home country is relatively high.
就是這個母國的水平是比較高的
then it has the power to come
然後它有力量來
this
這個
to occupy this colony
來佔領這塊殖民地
Then let the benefit of this colony
然後讓這個殖民地的利益
Serve home country
為母國服務
this is a
這個是一個
This one from the end of the 19th century
19世紀末開始的這個
an imperialist architecture
一個帝國主義的架構
under that framework
在那個架構下
so we can talk about colonies
我們才能夠去談殖民地
But treat the national government as a colonist
但是把國民政府當作殖民者
raised it a bit too much
有點太抬高它了
because it has no mother country
因為它沒有母國
it is defeated
它就是被打敗了
retreat to a very deep
撤退到一個非常深淑的
one without governance
一個沒有治理
It has only been governed for four years
才治理了四年的
a god brought back
收回來的一個神
In fact, when the National Government accepted the Northeast
其實國民政府在接受東北的時候
also encountered similar trouble
也碰到有類似的麻煩
I guess it's the price of saying something like this
我想它的這樣子的說法的代價
and then at the same time its level of development
然後同時它的發展水準
Not particularly high compared to Taiwan
相對於台灣也沒有特別高
The point is not just saying
重點是不只是這樣的說法
1. Once you describe the national government as a colonist
一你一旦把國民政府說成是殖民者
you don't
你就沒有
no way to point to the real colonists
沒有辦法指認真正的殖民者
Then you have no way to recognize our own place
那你就沒有辦法去認識到我們自己的位置
you won't identify
你就不會去指認
You will not point out that Japan was once our colonizer
你就不會去指認日本曾經是我們的殖民者
then America to now
然後美國到現在
still our important supporter
還是我們重要的支持者
if you think about it
如果大家想一想
It's true that we don't usually talk like this
確實我們平常沒有這樣子的言論
we only hear
我們只聽到說
The national government is a foreign regime and a colonial regime
國民政府是外來政權是一個殖民政權
we won't say what japan is like
我們不會說日本是怎麼樣
how is america
美國是怎麼樣
At the same time, there is no way to realize that
同時這樣子也沒有辦法認識到說
When developing the economy in a backward country
落後國家中要發展經濟的時候
its role in economic democracy
它的經濟民主主義的作用
this
這個
This way of thinking is different from what we have now
這樣子的看法跟我們現在
very relevant
非常有關係
Because our biggest difficulty now is how to get rid of
因為我們現在最大的一個難關是怎麼樣去
Facing mainland China
面對中國大陸
Then we are now the mainstream
那我們現在主流
is to continue the framework
是延續這樣的框架
the national government
就是國民政府
original enemy number one
原來的第一號敵人
now enemy number one
現在第一號敵人
to mainland China
就順延中國大陸
Also put it in a frame like this
也把它擺在這樣的一個框架裡面
but the problem is
但問題是
This is for us to plan
這樣子對於我們要去策劃
our economic future
我們的經濟未來
economic vision
經濟願景
only brings difficulties
只會帶來困難
Because mainland China
因為中國大陸
It also
它也
In fact, the economic benefits to the present
其實經濟利益到現在
did not enter Taiwan
也沒有進入台灣
its level of development
它的發展水平
not higher than Taiwan
並不比台灣高
It is Taiwan that is exporting capital
是台灣在輸出資本
manpower to the mainland
人力到大陸去
so
所以
Such a structure allows us to understand
這樣的架構讓我們去理解
National Government
國民政府
to understand
去理解
Now the number one enemy is mainland China
現在的頭號敵人中國大陸
are in the way
都是有妨礙的
that's what i'm saying
這就是我要說
we have no way to go
我們沒有辦法去
If you face this problem
面對這個問題的話
is the prospect of hindering our development
是會妨礙我們的發展的前景
well that
好 那
ok let's see
好 我們看一下
the national government
這個國民政府
After retreating to Taiwan in a disastrous defeat
在慘敗中退守台灣之後的
doing
所作所為
First he did a very important thing
首先他做了一件很重要的事情
land reform
就是土地改革
I enter
我進
I also observed that in recent years
我也觀察到近年來
There is a very
台灣學界有一個很
In line with this democratization
就配合著這樣民主化
and such a statement
以及這樣的一個論述
there is a share
有一股
The voice is to deny land reform
聲音是去否定土地改革
That
那
Or
或者說
Land reform is a foreign regime
土地改革就是外來政權
But the problem is the foreign regime
但問題是外來政權
It is not necessary to do land reform, is it?
也不一定要做土地改革 是不是
Japan Comes to Taiwan Although Tibetan Land Cancels Big Tenants
日本到臺灣來雖然藏人的土地取消了大租戶
But he didn't go further to do real land reform did he?
但是他沒有進一步做真正的土地改革是不是
So foreign regimes and land reform
所以外來政權與土地改革
Foreign regimes may make land reform easier
外來政權或許讓土地改革比較容易
But that doesn't mean he's going to
但並不表示他要做
This is of course the communist revolution in mainland China
這個當然是中國大陸的共產革命
Under the Oppression of the Agrarian Revolution
土地革命的壓迫下
Let those who had no determination to do this do it
讓原來沒有決心去做這件事情的做了
But luckily with a compromise
但是幸好是以一種妥協的
Even the landlords in Taiwan actually compromised
就是臺灣的地主其實也妥協
did not rise up in rebellion
並沒有起來叛亂
So it's a three way compromise
所以是一個三方面妥協的一個
Land reform was carried out in a peaceful and stable manner
和平穩安定的方式進行了土地改革
Of course this is for Taiwan
這個當然有對臺灣
have a very important impact
有非常重要的影響
because we see
因為我們看看
Economic Development of COCO
COCO的經濟發展
Hundreds of years
幾百年
it's a long process
它過程很長
So how do we describe this development?
那我們怎麼樣去描述這個發展呢
of course it is
那當然是
the french revolution
就是法國大革命
Britain's Glorious Revolution
英國的光榮革命
is what to do
是做的是什麼
It is to overthrow the privileges of the feudal land aristocracy
就是把封建土地貴族的特權打倒
then let this
然後讓這個
The rise of the bourgeoisie who wants to do business and industrialize
要經商工業化的資產階級抬頭
That
那
Land Reform of the Nationalist Government
國民政府的土地改革
is a top-down
就是一種由上而下的
Bourgeois revolution
資產階級革命
then why would you do it
那為什麼會做呢
is led by the Communist Party of China
是在中國共產黨領導的
Under the pressure of the land revolution
土地革命的壓力下
Then it eliminates the left wing on the one hand
那它以一方面的肅清左翼
It's 28 plus white terror
就是二八加上白色恐怖
pardon his opposition
恕親了他的反對勢力
then under this pressure
然後在這個壓力下
he did
他確實
in order to maintain power
為了保持政權
made some progress
做了一些比較進步的事情
including land reform
包括土地改革
ok so look at that
好 那麼看一下就是說
this
這個
Did the Nationalist Government establish a monopoly in Taiwan after the war?
國民政府是不是在戰後在台灣建立了壟斷性的
party-state capitalism
黨國資本主義
Since 1991, Chen Simeng
我們自1991年陳思孟
the six
這個六位
Facility Economist
陳設經濟學者
Wrote a book called Deconstructing Party-State Capitalism
寫了一本書叫做解構黨國資本主義
is a very famous book
是非常有名的一本書
that he
那他
It represents such a one of our economics
代表了就是我們經濟學的這樣的一個
free market theory
自由市場的理論跟
this democracy
這民主
To push is to overthrow authority
推就是要推翻威權
with a nice combination
有了一個很好的結合
so he was very successful
所以他很成功的
brought a term called party-state capitalism
帶來了一個名詞叫做黨國資本主義
so from that
所以從那個
very successful
非常的成功
Since then we have listened
從那個以後我們就聽
Just got the name
就是有了這個名詞了
party-state capitalism
黨國資本主義
but let's see
但是我們看一下
Is it true? If all the KMT did was create a
是真的嗎如果國民黨所做的事情只是建立一個
Monopoly
壟斷性的
The party-state capital
這個黨國資本
How can Taiwan still be able to develop?
那台灣怎麼可能還能夠發展
that would be a real miracle
那才會是真的是奇蹟
That's actually
那其實
We can understand it by overcoming fear
我們可以以藉勝恐懼來理解
the national government
這個國民政府
So he received monopoly Japanese capital
所以他接收了壟斷性的日資
Large enterprises remain state-owned but do not expand further
大型企業保留為國營企業但是不進一步擴張
Taiwan Sugar
就是台糖
Taipower
台電
CNPC what
中油什麼什麼
Most of the emerging parts are open to the private sector
那新興的部分多半都開放民營
so
所以
so i'll wait
所以我等一下會
show two pictures
秀兩個圖
One is that in the 1950s, manufacturing and industry
一個就是到了五零年代製造業跟工業
The proportion of private enterprises has exceeded half
民營的比例已經過半
at the same time
同時
Taiwan's main private capital
台灣主要的私人資本
are new post-war
都是戰後新興的
This picture is very obvious
這個圖非常明顯
This is it
就是這個
this is industry
這是工業
1958 crossover
1958年交叉
So this private
所以這個私營
keep rising
就不斷的上升
The labor camp continued to decline
工營就不斷的下降
ok let's see
好 我們看一下
This is based on the Chinese Faith Institute
這個是依據中華真信所
it came out in 2008
它出的2008年
Top 50 Group Enterprises in Taiwan
台灣地區前50大集團企業
Then according to their founding years
然後依據他們的創始年代
take a look
來看一下
Only 5 are from before 1945
只有5家是1945年之前的
It was very small before
這個之前也是非常小
for example
譬如說
For example, Big Companion
譬如說大同伴
may be
可能就是
a small iron factory
一個小小的鐵工廠
I think this mountain should be
我想這個山應該是
There is also a telecommunications bureau
還有一個電信局
Another one is Wan Hai
還有一個是萬海
Then the mainland came to Taiwan
然後大陸來台
one is the same bureau
一個是照樣局
Later changed its name to Yang Ming Shipping
後來改名陽明海運
Because the mainland also has a bureau
因為大陸也有個照樣局
This was established during the Qing Dynasty
這個是清朝時候設立的
The other is the Far East
另外一個是遠東
good
好
So that is
所以也就是
see is say
看到就是說
Traditional industries in the 1950s and 1960s
五零年代六零年代的傳統產業
and the financial industry
以及金融業
Cathay Pacific Yuanshou
就是國泰元壽
what starlight yuanshou
什麼星光元壽
These are mainly domestic market
這些以國內市場為主的
traditional manufacturing and service industries
傳統製造以及服務業
twenty
二十家
Another big one is the high-tech industry
另外一個大宗是高科技業
Of course we know that he came after the 1970s
當然我們知道他是七零年代後來
established
成立的
For example, like Shi Zhenrong, Lin Baili, Guo Taiming
都是譬如說像施振榮 林百里 郭台銘
These are the postwar
這些都是戰後受
He may not be born after the war
他不一定戰後出身
but educated after the war
但是是戰後受教育的
Lin Baili once said
曾經時候林百里還說
National Taiwan University's Department of Electrical Engineering failed very badly
台大電機系教育非常地失敗
But let's look at their generation
但是我們看一看他們那一代
His class is amazing
他那一班不得了
He opened with his classmates
他就跟他的同學合開
so successful
那麼地成功
so i don't know if he is
所以我不知道他是
what about his accusations
他的指責有怎麼說
we are hard to measure
我們難以衡量
so their generation
所以他們這一代
Taiwan's postwar-educated generation of engineers
台灣戰後受教育的這一代的工程師
Help Taiwan build high-tech
幫助台灣建立了高科技
ok so this shows
好 所以這個就顯示
that's what i just said
就是我剛說的
Taiwan's main private capital is post-war star
台灣主要私人資本都是戰後星星的
This is what I originally said
這個就是跟我原來說的
Modern Industry in the Japanese Occupation Era
日據時代的現代工業
Mainly Japanese
主要是日資
and no japan
並沒有日本
did not train
並沒有培養
Cultivate local modern industry in Taiwan
在台灣培養本地的現代工業
It's dependent
這是相依智的
At the same time he also shows
同時他也顯示
After the fearful national government came to Taiwan
戒勝恐懼的國民政府到了台灣之後
He is not like those authors say
他並沒有像那些作者所說的
just means support
只是意味的扶植
party-state capitalism
黨國資本主義
ok let's look at this background
好 我們看看這個背景
good this
好 這個
This is the KMT-CCP struggle, line competition
這是國共鬥爭 路線競爭
After the Kuomintang-Communist cooperation began on 1923 24
從國共合作 1923 24 開始國共合作之後
Then they say
然後他們講件是
2627 After the Purge
2627 清黨之後
The Kuomintang and the Communist Party started like this
國共兩黨就開始了這樣子
a very tough competition
一個非常慘烈的競爭
To seize the power to lead China's modernization
要奪取領導中國現代化的權力
We know that the national government failed miserably
我們知道國民政府慘敗
Let's look at 1949
我們看一下1949年
January 1949
1949年1月
Chen Cheng Street Audit Chairman
陳誠街審主席
At that time, the People's Liberation Army was preparing to cross the Yangtze River
那個時候人民解放軍正準備要渡長江
just practice water combat first
只是先要練習一下水戰
ship first
先要艦船
So at that time we can negotiate
所以那個時候就可以和談
There are eight conditions for peace talks
和談有八大條件
Land reform Confiscation of bureaucratic capital
土地改革 沒收官僚資本
Great Traitor Treaty
傑出賣國條約
The Mai Guo Treaty is the 1946 passage I just mentioned
邁國條約就是我剛說的1946的通行
So when Chen Cheng took over Chairman God in January
所以陳誠一月接神主席的時候
He said there's little to die for from here
他說 離此一步 幾無死所
I think it can better show their mood at that time.
我想就比較可以顯現他們那個時候的心情
he did a lot that year
他在那一年做了很多事情
He immediately announced the implementation of the 375 inspection
他立即宣布實施三七五檢註
no legal basis
沒有法律根據
he just does
他就說就做
It is true that the construction started in the first quarter of the year
那確實那一年第一季到做就開始建築
I've never acted like this
從來沒有這樣子雷厲風行過
But Taiwan's conditions are better
但是也是台灣的條件比較好
allow him to do this
讓他可以這樣做
Reform avoids wisdom
改革避智
Exchange Taiwan Dollars for New Taiwan Dollars
就台幣換新台幣
Then start setting up a committee to plan Home Rule
然後開始設立個委員會規劃地方自治
promulgate martial law
頒布戒嚴令
There will be an official signing at the end of the year
還有年底正式簽臺
finally reform party affairs
終於改革黨務
then white terror
然後白色恐怖
Qing left wing
清左翼
ok then i
好 那我
Now I'm going to turn to this part of the economy
現在我要轉到這個經濟的部分
At that time it was really stormy
在那個時候真的是風雨飄搖中
Economic crisis continues Hyperinflation
經濟危機不斷 惡性通貨膨脹
fiscal deficit trade deficit
財政赤字 貿易赤字
Lack of foreign exchange Lack of supplies
外匯缺乏 物資缺乏
population and food pressure
人口與糧食的壓力
Then I think everyone should
那我想這個大家應該都
full of familiarity
滿熟悉的
One or two million people immigrated from the mainland
從大陸遷來了一兩百萬人
population pressure food pressure
人口的壓力 糧食的壓力
Then
然後
Lack of money, lack of supplies, lack of foreign exchange
缺錢 缺物資 缺外匯
Although a shipment of gold
雖然運來了一批黃金
but
但是
middle
中
just keep selling
就是不斷的賣
You can see that its stock is constantly decreasing
你就看到它的存量不斷的減少
So this is very
所以這個是非常
It is indeed a state of economic crisis
確實是一個經濟危機的狀態
But we see that within two or three years
但是我們看到兩三年內
Indeed, these bureaucrats
確實這一批官僚
Ying Chongrong, Yan Jiagai, etc.
影重榮 嚴家蓋等等
They did stabilize the situation
他們確實把情況穩定下來了
By 1952
到了1952年
Production returns to its highest level
生產恢復到佔前最高水平
Prices start to stabilize
物價開始穩定
at the same time
同時
Although the population has increased by one or two million
人口雖然增加了一兩百萬
However, food is generally stable
但糧食大致大致穩定
but i want to say
但我要說
Although the dollar plays an important role
雖然美元扮演了很重要的角色
but
但是
not all
不是全部
because you have dollars
因為你有了美元
like forty five to forty nine with dollars
就像四五到四九有了美元
you can mess up too
你也可以搞得一塌糊塗
It's also a mess on the mainland
同樣在大陸搞得一團亂的
a mess, a fiasco
一塌糊塗的慘敗的
The national government came to relatively small Taiwan
國民政府到了比較小的台灣
indeed overcome fear
確實藉勝恐懼
those are capable
那這些有能力
The financial bureaucrat came out ahead with his energy and job base
財經官僚以他的能量跟工作基校出頭了
to dominate economic affairs
得以主導經濟事務
like pampering eye gel lids and more
像以縱容眼膠蓋等等
ok then take a look
好 那麼看一下
The source of these talents
這些人才的來源
get to know them
來瞭解一下他們
their background
他們的背景
their thoughts
他們的想法
that is to say why am I talking
就是說我為什麼要談
What about these talents?
這些人才呢
It's because of the constant chaos at this time
是因為這個時候不斷亂
At the same time we need to know
同時我們要知道
The national government is indeed compared to the Japanese colonial government
國民政府確實相較於日本殖民政府
it is indeed a degree of modernization
它確實是一個現代化程度
Organization is relatively low
組織比較低
poor organizational skills
組織能力比較差
A government with a relatively weak system
制度比較不健全的一個政府
We can say a semi-modern government
我們可以說是一個半現代化的政府
So the role of these people is even more important
那因此這些人的角色就更行重要
Thanks
謝謝
Let's take a look at the resource committee
我們看一下資源委員會
Because he is a cradle of talent
因為他是一個人才的搖籃
It is the Tsinghua War in Japan
就是日本清華戰爭
It is a very, very important event for China
對於中國是一個非常非常重要的事件
has its incredible effect
有它不得了的影響
Around 1932
到了1932年前後
That is, 918 in Japan has already happened
就是日本918已經發生
one or two years
一兩年
then there is already
然後已經有
The situation of invading North China
要入侵華北的這種情勢
So there was a saying at that time
所以那個時候有句話
That is, the North China University of Finance and Economics can no longer fit a peaceful desk
就是華北資大已經放不下一張平靜的書桌
that seems to be
那個好像是
The student movement at that time was a famous saying
那個時候的學運的是一個名言
So in 1932 the national government established the National Defense Design Committee
所以1932年國民政府成立國防設計委員會
some hopeful intellectuals
一些具慶望的知識分子
in Beijing
在北京的
Big intellectuals are also willing to start willing to join
大知識分子也願意開始願意加入
Then start teaching and inspecting minerals
然後開始教察礦產
what about
什麼怎麼樣
In 1935, it was changed to the Resources Committee and the German
1935年改為資源委員會跟德國
cooperation with nazi germany
納粹德國合作
then this
然後這個
Ke Weilin
這很有名的漢學家柯偉麟
Wang Fu must be very familiar
王富一定很熟悉
He is famous for speaking
他的成名之作就是講
Cooperation between Nazi Germany and Chiang Kai-shek's Nationalist Government
納粹德國跟蔣介石國民政府的合作
because after the war
因為一戰之後
Germany lost any privileges of his imperialism
德國失去了他帝國主義的任何特權
so he becomes a
所以他變成是一個
non-imperialist advanced country
非帝國主義的先進國
only
唯一的
So he is very willing to follow
所以他非常願意跟
Willing to help the Republic of China at that time
願意幫助那個時候的中華民國
to build a military industry
來建立軍事工業
what training
什麼訓練
train the army like this
訓練軍隊這樣
Just help me fight Japan in the future
就幫忙以後打日本的
good
好
it's really helpful
就是確實是有很大的幫助
on fairly good terms
以相當好的條件
He mainly goes to change some
他主要去換一些
this rare
這個稀有
metal
有金屬
During this two-person war
這次二人會戰爭時期
is responsible for establishing
就負責建立
we can see it was done in 1935
我們可以看到1935年才做
Maybe Japan saw
或許日本看了
I think it's time to do it
就覺得該動手了
I have no idea
我不知道
1937 was like the Juqiao Incident
1937就如鞠橋事變了
so don't have much time to do too much
所以沒有太多時間做太多事情
Wartime MC is in the rear
戰爭時間資委會就在後方
build some industries
建立一些工業
after america entered the war
美國參戰之後
after pearl harbor
珍珠港事件之後
beauty is coming
美人就來了
after that
那個之後
The committee can send someone to
資委會就可以派人到
The United States went to the commission
美國去授訊
front and rear
前後
More than 500 people were sent
派了500多人
so a very big person
所以是非常大的一個人
very important thing
很重要的一件事情
first batch
第一批
they formed
他們成立了
Later, the 31 Society was established
後來成立了31學社
Because there are 31 people
因為就是31個人
in may
在5月
May 31
5月31號
Then it seems to have forgotten
然後好像是忘了哪
exist
在
It seems to be May 31st
好像是5月31號
set up their 3-one society
成立他們的3一學社
who does that include
那包括誰呢
Shun Xuan
順應璇
Also including Wang An
也包括王安
Later, Wang An Computer was established in the United States.
就後來在美國建立王安電腦了
Wang An
王安
Just this tiny tree
就這一片極小樹
Wang Anliu
向王安留在
stay in america
留在美國
Most of them returned to the mainland
絕大部分都回到大陸
So after they got to Pearl Harbor
所以他們到珍珠港之後
such training
這樣的訓練
helped China cultivate
幫中國培育了
a lot of money
一筆很重要
very important talent
很重要的人才
Then they simultaneously start doing
然後他們同時開始做
economic planning
經濟規劃
Just after the war
就戰後
what kind of industry are we going to build
我們要建立什麼樣的工業
how to receive
要怎麼樣去接收
what kind of new
要怎麼樣的新建
What kind of new industry will be built, etc.
要蓋什麼樣的新的工業什麼等等
very
很
in their plans
在他們的計劃中
There are two places that are very important
有兩塊地方非常的重要
One is of course the Northeast
一個當然是東北
because
因為
because this
因為這個
in Japan
日本在
Because China was really poor at that time
因為中國那個時候真的很可憐
no industry
沒有什麼工業
this
這個
mostly in the northeast
大部分在東北
another piece
另外一塊呢
in Taiwan
在台灣
good
好
We know that there is a big problem with Northeast reception
我們知道東北接收出現了很大的問題
Russia
俄國
japanese american what these
日本 美國 什麼這些
but
但是
Taiwan's reception is very
台灣的接收非常的
very successful
非常地成功
at least voluntary committee
至少自願委員會
with the Chief Executive's Office
跟行政長官公署的
Perfect teamwork
合作無間
received
接收了
Relatively large
比較大的
enterprise
企業
voluntary committees in the national government
自願委員會是在國民政府中
should be a better
應該是一個比較好的
this piece
這一塊
Emphasis on professional enterprise talent cultivation
強調專業化企業化人才培育
Absorbed excellent science and engineering talents
吸收了優秀理工人才
relatively sound system
體制比較的健全
Their
他們的
Of course, the previous photo was talking to Chiang Kai-shek
當然 前張照就是跟蔣介石講說
Refuse the party's influence to enter
拒絕黨的勢力進入
Don't send your CC pies what pies come in
不要派你的CC派 什麼派進來
and successfully rejected
而成功的拒絕了
let it be a
讓它是一個
but also because of this
但是也因此
The committee for
資委會對於
last so corrupt
最後的那麼腐敗
The soon-to-be-failing national government was particularly disappointed
即將失敗的國民政府特別失望
So the committee is
所以資委會是
The only unit that is not as good as the investment
唯一不及投共的單位
so most people stay
所以大部分人留在
stay on the mainland
留在大陸
You say Li Guoding and Sun Yunxuan are
你說李國鼎 孫運璇是
Are you here to vote for Taiwan?
特別來投台灣嗎
no they are
不是 他們是
sent earlier
比較早就派到
Taiwan to receive Taiwan
台灣來接收台灣
good so
好 所以
The capital committee came to receive
資委會來來接收
Top 10 companies established by Japanese-funded enterprises
日資企業成立十大公司
their reception is better
他們的接收做得比較好
it is a pity
很可惜
The national government will not send them to receive
國民政府不會派他們去接收
Research Commons
研究公賣局
Otherwise, there shouldn't be such a mess
不然就應該不會出那種亂子
So it's better for them to receive more productive grades
所以他們接收更富產的成績就比較好
After
在之後
These large-scale talents of the Self-committee are the cross-strait
自委會大型的這些人才是兩岸
At the same time, it is the foundation of state-owned enterprises on both sides of the strait
同時是兩岸國營企業的基礎
so
所以
So if we look at
所以如果我們去看一下
Older state-owned enterprises in the mainland
大陸比較老的國營企業
Compared with the old public enterprises in Taiwan
跟現在台灣的老的公營企業
you see a lot of similarities
你看到有很多類似之處
When everyone is driving, go to refuel
大家開車的話去加油的時候
please pay attention
請大家注意一下
Medium oil
中油
CNPC doesn't have a logo
中油不是有一個標誌
there is a word below
下面有一個字
That's the word committee
那就是這個字委會
Okay, so after the war in Taiwan
好 所以台灣戰後
Eight of the top 15 economic ministers
前15位經濟部長8位
from self-committee
來自自委會
Rong Li Guoding in the movie
影中榮李國鼎
Sun Yuxuan
孫玉璇
Zhao Yaodong
趙耀東
Li Danghai and so on
李當海等等
good
好
Then I will be honored in the movie
那我以影中榮
As an example
作為一個例子
Come
來
speaking of this generation
來講這一代人
then i say this
那我說這個
not to
並不是要
what kind of personality cult
要來建立什麼個人崇拜
or what kind of meaning
或什麼最類的意思
but to explain
而是要解釋
in this way
這樣子
a historical background
一個歷史背景
to explain
來說明說
Against such a historical background
在那樣一個歷史背景之下
this group of people
這批人
Have such a great sense of mission
有這麼樣大的使命感
to help Taiwan
才幫助台灣
in that chaos
在那個樣子的亂局中
Laid the foundation for future development
奠立了未來發展的基礎
good
好
then I will start with
那我先以
so here's what i'm saying
所以這就是我要說的
that is
就是說
In addition to ability
除了能力之外
ability
能力
Of course it's important
當然很重要
work performance
就是他們以工作積效
there is a crisis
就是有了危機
they can handle
他們可以處理
in mainland period
在大陸時期
This kind of people fight lightly
這種人士輕壓鬥爭
yes of course
是當然
always serious
向來是很嚴重的
So those who are capable may not be able to stand out
所以有能力的人未必可以出頭
but in the last days
但是在最後初期
This heightened sense of crisis
這種高度的危機感
make the ruler
使得主政者
willing
願意
or he feels he must
或者他覺得必須
to those who can
給這些有能力的人
right
權利
I take the exempt occupation as an example
我以免訪職業為例子
I just want to use this to illustrate
我就是要用這個來說明
Will to develop
發展的意志
1951 to 53
1951到53
There is a program called
有一個program叫做
To be visited
待訪待知
can be complicated to explain
要解釋起來可能很複雜
but in simple terms
但簡單的來講
imitation means
代仿的意思就是說
government takes care of everything
政府負責一切
took American cotton
拿了美國的棉花
Giving room battlefield
給房沙場
It's like giving you a sum
就等於給你一筆
OEM money
代工錢
Then after the room is sandy
然後房好沙了之後
back to the government
又回到政府
The government put the housing good sand
政府又把房好的沙
Take it to the branch factory
拿給支部廠
then pay another
然後又付一筆支
branch fee
支部費
then back again
然後又收回來
Then the cloth that was brought back
然後收回來的這個布
Then give the marketing system
然後再給了行銷體系
resend
再發出去
So it's called generation imitation generation branch
所以就叫代仿代支
highly dominant
高度的主導
this
這個
The choice of the man in the movie was at that time
影中人的選擇是那個時候
he said it was
他就說這是
war time
戰爭時候
war economy
戰時經濟
then the mainland
然後大陸
Chitai
千台
Mainland China
大陸千台
This one from Shanghai Qiantai
上海千台的這個
Fangsadin
這個房沙定
has come
已經來了
how many million
多少萬定
this is already existing
這個是已經既有的
then i will
那我就
give priority to supporting them
優先的扶植他們
because
因為
yes no more
對 不需要再
Use foreign exchange to buy Dingding, Dingding, etc.
外匯去買殺定 訪定等等
Therefore, the priority is to support the mainland to lead Taiwan to visit the killing field
所以優先扶植大陸牽臺 訪殺場
Then so now imagine this
然後所以現在可以想像這個
How much controversy can be caused
可以引起多大的爭議
but he did
但他就做了
So when he was visiting the capital
所以他在代訪代資的時候
made a high degree of trade-off
是做了高度的取捨
made a lot of decisions
做了很多的決定
and then there are highly criticized
然後有高度 受到高度的批評
For example, like Lei Zhen's Free China
譬如說像雷震的自由中國
I also saw articles criticizing him
我也看到文章在批評他
then say
然後說
because we can imagine saying
因為我們可以想像說
how much trouble can happen
可以出多少亂子
That's the one someone secretly sold
就是這個有人偷偷賣出去
Somebody profited from it, what, what, what
有人從中得利 有什麼什麼這些
At the same time, give priority to supporting the leading Taiwan in the mainland
同時優先扶植大陸的牽臺
visit killing field
訪殺場
There are also articles criticizing Free China
向自由中國也有文章來批評說
How can Taiwan have such a scale to develop imitation teacher industry
台灣哪有這種規模可以發展仿師業
might as well import
還不如進口
So on that example
所以在那個例子上
I think Free China may not be right
我覺得自由中國可能未必是對的
but it's messy
但雖然很混亂
But in the summer of 1953
但是到了1953年夏天
succeeded two years later
兩年之後成功了
achieved autonomy
達到了自己自主
at the same time
同時
Wu Zhongrong immediately announced the end of this Program
吳仲榮就立即宣布這個Program結束
That is to say, for these
也就是說他對於這些
It turns out that he fostered the support of the object
原來的他扶植了對象的支持
he tested
他就測了
At the same time, gradually open up new manufacturers to enter
同時逐步開放新廠商進入
promote market competition
促進市場競爭
Slowly Tainan Bang also came in
慢慢的台南邦也進來了
what wait
什麼等等
So four years later
所以到了四年後
is completely open
就是完全開放了
he used to have
他曾經有
During this process
在這個過程中
he once said
他曾經有句話說
The factory is not ready yet
工廠尚未籌備就序
written agreement
請求保護之成文一致
The product is not yet in large quantities literally
產品尚未大量硬是
The request to restrict the establishment of factories has been put forward
限制設廠之要求已經提出
so
所以
So it means that in this process
所以就表示說在這個過程中
individual
個別
Manufacturers are constantly asking
廠商不斷地去要求
Your protection of me continues
你對我的保護繼續維持
so
這樣
no matter what
不管是說是
I this this is all kinds of protection
我這個這個是各種各樣的保護
but he ended up
但是他最後
open all
就全部開放
So what I'm saying is that he set up various individual interest requirements
所以我這樣說的是他立牌各種個別利益要求
petition basis for dating
約會的請願依據
The benefits of overall long-term development come in the form of
整體長期發展的利益來形式
of course
那當然
Offended a lot of people in the process
這過程中得罪很多人
good
好
Let me continue with the example
我再繼續說明這個例子
it was in 1951
它在1951年
it said a famous saying
它就講了一句很有名的話
Imported cloth is not as good as imported yarn
叫做進口布不如進口紗
Imported yarn is not as good as imported flowers
進口紗不如進口花
put down cotton juice
要放下棉紡汁
It is not as good as upstream and downstream to develop together
不如上下遊一起發展
It is cotton and then put raw yarn
就是棉花然後放生紗
Yarn sausage is a relatively capital-intensive
紗紗腸是一個比較資本密集的
this production activity
這個生產活動
and then after yarn
然後放紗之後
then there is branch cloth
然後有支布
Cloth
支布
Although at that time
雖然那個時候
Of course, it is all powered by cloth
當然都是用動力支布
But it can be smaller
但是規模可以比較小
So yarn sausage and cloth sausage are separated
所以紗紗腸跟支布腸是分開來的
That is to say
也就是說
They are upstream and downstream
他們是上下遊
interests between them
他們之間的利益
there will be conflict
會有衝突
good
好
So it has to develop a set of
所以它就必須發展出一套
To reconcile the interests of upstream and downstream
去調和上下遊利益的做法
So it is giving upstream
所以它在給予上遊
Sasa
就紗紗
While providing trade protection
提供貿易保護的同時
it for it
它對於它
Its price, quality and protection period are limited
它的價格品質跟保護期限做出限制
that is
就是說
good
好
you can act like a fool
你可以仿傻了
Then I'll give you two or three years of protection
那我給你兩年或三年的保護
Protection means I restrict imports
保護的意思就是我限制進口
But your quality must meet the downstream needs
但是你的品質要符合下游的需要
branch factory needs
支部廠的需要
At the same time your price cannot exceed
同時你的價格不能超過
25% of the import price
進口價格的25%
for example
譬如說這樣
So you see this is a
所以你看看到這是一個
I study economic development
我研究經濟發展
I think it's a very important
我覺得這是一個很重要的
institutional innovation
制度的創新
its protection is conditional
它的保護是有條件
There is a deadline
有期限
i just said
我剛剛講了
that is two or three years
就是說兩年或三年
Then your price cannot exceed
然後你的價格不能超過
How much is the international price
國際價格多少
Then your quality should be in a reasonable range
然後你的品質要在一個合理的範圍
Can't say that downstream comes to quarrel with me every day
不能說下游天天來跟我吵
say your disagreement
說你的不合
But if you're in the range
但是如果你在這個範圍內
if possible
可以的話
Downstream must endure for two years
下游就必須忍受兩年
so this is a set
所以這個是一套
what say this is
什麼說這個是
An innovation made by Taiwan
台灣做出來的一個創新
Of course, South Korea also imitated this later.
這個當然後來南韓也模仿了這個
So this is the East Asian model
所以這個是東亞模式
The key to outperforming Latin America
優於拉丁美洲的關鍵
It means that the protection is limited and conditional
就是保護有期限有條件
You didn't protect your childish industry and couldn't grow up
你沒有保護你這個幼稚工業長不起來
But if your protection lasts
但是你保護一直存續的話
it doesn't grow
它就不長進
so this is
所以這個是
that time in difficult times
那個時候在困難時期
it is based on actual needs
它基於實際的需要
solve this problem
解決這個問題
It's not signing money
它也不是簽財
But it really wants to solve the problem
但是它真的想解決這個問題
so they don't stop it
因此他們也不止它
they figured out this way
他們想出這樣的辦法
Later also legislated
後來也立法了
there is such a law
就有這樣一個法
So its principals have a clear vision for development
所以它主事者有清楚的發展願景
is to make Taiwan
就是要使台灣
Complete the great cause of establishing a modern industrial production system
完成建立現代工業生產系統的大業
so he has a clear vision
所以他有一個清楚的願景
Therefore, except in the 500th generation, he
因此他除了在五零零代
In addition to the development of tied branches and leaves in the way of integration from top to bottom
除了以上下整合方式發展綁枝葉之外
He also started to promote the original fiber in the 500 generation
他也在五零零代已經開始推動原造纖維
Do we grow up in Taiwan and feel that it should be like this?
我們生長在台灣會覺得本來就應該這樣子嗎
what's the big deal
有什麼了不起呢
Isn't that the way things should be?
不是事情就應該這樣做嗎
But if we look at other backward countries
但是如果我們去看其他的落後國家
We found out that except for South Korea
我們就發現說除了南韓之外
no other country does this
沒有別的國家是這樣做的
That is, other countries use US dollars to import and kill
就是其他國家都是用美元進口殺
or imported cloth
或者進口布
Unlike Taiwan and South Korea
而沒有像台灣跟南韓
cotton is imported in US dollars
是用美元進口棉花
like pakistan and india
像巴基斯坦跟印度
they produce their own good
他們自己產很好的
They have also developed a non-visit industry
他們也發展了免訪之業
But after the development, they are busy fighting each other.
但發展完了他們就忙著互相打仗去了
So there is no further development
所以就也沒有進一步的發展
not like Taiwan
不像台灣的
Because of the development of exemption from visits, the development of rash
因為發展了免訪之有發展染疹
Dr. Chen, then Immortal, then Mixed Defense, etc.
陳醫 然後人仙 然後混防什麼什麼
all the way down
一路下來
So like now we have many
所以像現在我們有很多
like plastic bottles or something
譬如說保特瓶或什麼
Those are the original raw materials
那個都是原來的訪施原料
This is the Coliac
就是這個Coliac
what these started making plastic bottles
什麼這些就一開始做保特瓶
It's moved downstream
是下游外移了
upstream and start doing something else
上游就開始做點別的事
So Taiwan actually relies on this business of visiting
所以台灣其實靠這個訪之業
long meal
吃了很久的飯
moggy in wollin soon
到了伍林的莫吉很快的
Taiwan is indeed a small market
台灣確實市場很小
There is a surplus of non-visit business
免訪之業才能過剩
So 1960 had this
所以1960就有了這個
famous policy turn
很有名的政策轉折
From import substitution to export subsidies
從進口替代轉到出口補貼
Since then, Taiwan has entered into a rapidly growing export-led growth
從那個之後 臺灣進入了一個快速成長的出口導向的成長
Okay, so what I'm trying to emphasize here is that
好 所以我在這裡要強調的就是說
The concept and practice of this set of industrial policies after the war is a kind of institutional innovation
戰後這一套產業政策的理念跟做法是一種制度的創新
it's from them
那是源自於他們
At that time, I worked very hard to solve the crisis and difficulties at that time.
那個時候非常努力的要解決那個時候的危機跟困難
Then this set of practices laid the foundation for Taiwan's economic construction policy in the decades after the war
那這一套做法就奠定臺灣戰後數十年經濟建策的基礎
That is, our entire economy later
就是我們整個經濟後來
Later these
後來這些
The Beauty Association, the Work Committee, the Economic and Security Council are all merged into the Ministry of Economic Affairs
這個美人會啊 工委會啊 經安會啊都併到經濟部
Then a part goes to the Ministry of Economic Affairs
然後一部分到經濟部
Then the predecessor of the Economic Association was established
然後後來就成立了經濟會的前身
Then this system continues to the present
然後這一套制度就延續到現在
Of course it's very different now
當然現在有很大的不同了
ok let me say it again
好 我再說一下
background of movie glory
影中榮的背景
that's what he's going to do
就是他要這樣做
Of course it will cost a lot
當然是要付出很大代價的
That is to say, I have just emphasized
就是說我剛剛已經強調了
That is to say, the national government at that time
就是說那個時候的國民政府
yes it's still confusing
是還是很混亂的
This system is not perfect
這個制度不健全
The organization is not perfect
組織也不健全各種各樣
Then we Chinese are very good at putting pressure on each other
然後我們中國人很會互相輕壓
Guan Qiang's light pressure is happy once
官強輕壓是喜起來有次
So Ying Zhongrong's style
所以影中榮這種作風
Of course I made a lot of enemies
當然樹立了很多的敵人
So he was accused in 1955
因此他在1955年就被告
Talking about the Yang Zimu financial case to benefit others
說楊子木財案 圖利他人
dismissed from office
就罷官
Then apparently he offended his officer too
然後顯然他也得罪了他的長官
So he didn't protect him
因此也沒有保他
So he was dismissed for two years
所以他就罷官兩年
but paid
但付出了
He still maintains his style
他仍然維持他的作風
is the courage to recognize
就是勇於認識
then take
然後都採取
make very high-risk decisions
都會做出非常高風險的決策
Then he was in 1953
那他在1953年
when writing a letter to a friend
給一個朋友寫信的時候
Talking about the country's crisis, I was born at the age of 50
講說國難位以我被年以50
as long as you can work hard
只要能夠奮身努力
another ten years
再幹十年
Even death is not courageous
雖死亦不算膽命
also with Cheng Chan
亦與成產
He did write this after
他確實寫了這個之後
died ten years ago
十年就過世了
Then he spent his life
那他平生以
Guo Songtao
郭松濤自曠
Guo Songtao was in the late Qing Dynasty
郭松濤是清末
The Westernized National Salvation Faction in the Xianghuai Army
香懷軍中的西化救國派
Ambassador to the UK
出使到英國做大使
wrote Jicheng
寫了寄誠
It is recommended to adopt the Western system
建議採用西方制度
then be infinite
然後被無限
dismissed from office and died in depression
罷官以至鬱鬱而終
So this is his example
所以這是他的榜樣
but
但是
but also his
但是也是他的
lessons learned
前車之鑒
Because Guo Songtao is not a good person
因為郭松濤做人不太好
after dismissal
罷官之後
Cursed his enemies in private
在私底下把他的敵人都罵透了
so difficult to recover
因此難以再起
So this Wu Zhongrong is
所以這個 吳仲榮就是
Being scolded off, being scolded all day or being scolded
被罵關了 被整天 或者被罵了
He doesn't scold anyone in private
他私底下一個人都不罵
So someone guessed
所以有人就猜測說
On the one hand, he takes Guo Zhongyou as an example
他這個一方面是以郭忠祐為榜樣
On the one hand, it is also a lesson from others
在一方面也是前車之鑒
Don't scold others in private, don't scold even one enemy
私底下不罵人 敵人一個不罵
sure enough
果然確實在起
From 1957 to 63 years after his death
從五七年到他過世的六三年
he served five years
他在服務五年
Indeed he has many enemies
確實他的敵人很多
After his death there was talk of an attack
他過世之後有人說要攻擊
some people objected
就有人反對
Some entrepreneurs say
有企業家說
We're going to start a foundation to raise money for him.
我們要搞一個基金會幫他募款
Someone rushed over and tore off the fundraising cloth
結果有人衝過去把募款布撕掉
so he does have his enemies
所以他確實有他的敵人
well that
好 那
but i take
但我是以
example in the movie
影中為例
but
但是
There are many other forces in the same period
同時代有諸多他力
That is, let's see him write this letter
就是我們看看他寫這個信
it's for his friends
是給他的朋友
They are of the same generation
就是他們同一輩
the same feelings
是同樣的情懷
they think we should
他們覺得我們就是應該
do something like this
做這樣的事情
so
所以
We must start from the background of this generation
我們必須從這代人的背景
to understand
去理解
So I call them
所以我把他們叫做
An official who serves the country through industry
以實業就國的如官
instead of
而不是
what we understand now
我們現在理解的
They seem to be more moral financial bureaucrats
他們好像道德比較好的財經官僚
I think
我覺得
It doesn't seem like this
這樣好像不
cannot fully represent their
不能夠完全代表他們的
this state
這種狀態
I
我
here is a big
這裡有一大
There are some
有一些
the case
案例
like what would he do
譬如說他會做什麼
high risk things
高風險的事情
For example once
譬如說有一次
A batch of imported materials
一批進口物資
Single brother due to tax dispute
因為稅款爭議而單哥
To keep these materials from rotting
為了免於這些物資因而腐爛
Take the initiative to provide guarantees by the CITIC Bureau
主動由中信局提供擔保
Then he repeatedly decided to get a loan from the CITIC Bureau
然後他一再決定由中信局貸款
For private enterprises in financial difficulties
給擲憂斷財務困難的民營企業
poplar wood
如楊子木材
Then, for example, he disregarded the opposition of the army
然後譬如說他不顧軍翻反對
Ritsu manufactures military shoes with Shinsan leather
立主用神產皮革製造軍用皮鞋
Develop leather industry
發展皮革工業
Against the objections of the Bureau of Zero Objects
不顧零物局反對
Import Liuwan, develop the deck industry, etc.
進口柳灣發展甲板工業等等等等
so he
所以他
He has the courage to make enemies and this cut
他勇於製造敵人跟這個裁取
we'll now feel like saying
我們會現在會覺得說
This kind of decision-making that seems to have the risk of benefiting others
好像會有圖利他人的這種風險的這種決策
and he
並且他
that is
就是
after dismissal
罷官結束之後
he still maintains
他仍然維持
such style
這樣子的作風
ok then i should close it soon
好 那我應該快要把它結束
so i just said
所以我剛剛已經說了
I'm not trying to make it into a cult individual
我並不是要把它變成一個值得崇拜的個人
is not what it means
不是這個意思
Rather, it must be under the background of that era
而是說必然是在那樣的時代的背景之下
Let them be a little reckless and do these things
讓他們有點憤不顧身的來做這些事情
their sense of mission
他們的使命感
Then that environment also needs such a person
然後那個環境也需要有這樣的人
Only in the absence of system and lack of organization
才能夠在那種缺乏制度缺乏組織
then an economy
然後一片經濟
Economically chaotic situation to solve the problem
經濟上一片混亂的狀況下去解決問題
and then fix the problem
然後再解決問題
in the process of problem solving
解決問題的過程中
Founded Taiwan
奠立了台灣
foundation of economic development
經濟發展的基礎
so
所以
So the process is very dependent on
所以這個過程是非常依靠
motivation of these people
這些人的動力
And then I'm going to talk about their motivation
然後我要說的是他們的動力
originate from
源自於
Inheritance of the Old Wang Tucheng of Chinese Intellectuals
中國知識分子舊王圖城的傳承
and during the KMT-CCP struggle
以及國共鬥爭中他們
By the National Government
靠國民政府這邊
their disastrous experience
他們的慘敗的經驗
and because they were
然後因為他們是被
Defeated by the revolution of the Communist Party of China
中國共產黨的革命所擊敗
so they borrow sex fear
所以他們藉性恐懼
purge the left
一方面肅清左翼
white terror very bloody
白色恐怖非常血腥
but on the other hand
但另外一方面
Also use the fear of sex to follow the Three People's Principles
也藉性恐懼的走三民主義式的
The development model of military endowment
軍賦的發展模式
At the same time, due to land reform
同時因為土地改
this china
這個中國
The Land Reform of the Communist Party of China The Success of the Land Revolution
中國共產黨土地改革 土地革命的成功
made them attach great importance to agriculture
使得他們非常重視農業
So throughout the 1950s and 1960s
所以整個五零年代六零年代
sixty
六零
Mainly the 1950s for agriculture
主要是五零年代 對於農業
is very important
是非常重視
part of agriculture
農業的部分
Agricultural Restoration
農復會
The Peasant Rehabilitation Conference is also ours
農復會也是我們也可以
tell a similar story
說一套同樣差不多類似的故事
but of course he has his price
但是當然有他的代價
just cleared the left wing
就是清除了左翼
So this is the disappearance of the left eye
所以這個是左眼消失
This is Chen Yingzhen
這個是陳映真
is our famous writer
就是我們有名的文學家
his terms
他的用語
that is to say he said
就是說他說
Taiwan is a society where the left eye does not disappear
台灣是一個沒有左眼消失的社會
The left eye may not be very important
左眼可能不是很重要
But your lack of a left eye is an imbalance
但是你缺乏左眼就是不平衡
ok so i gave them a name
好 所以我給他們取了一個名字
They are not just economic bureaucrats
他們不只是經濟官僚
It is the traditional intellectuals who save the country with industry and save the nation.
而是以工業救國 救亡 徒存的傳統知識分子
Finally, let me talk about the hardworking people
最後我講一下努力的人民
because i didn't just say
因為我剛不是講
In our mainstream discourse, there are three
我們的主流論述裡面有三個
Either Japan or the United States or the people
就是或者日本 或者美國 或者人民
but of course our people work hard
但是我們的人民當然很努力
We are still working hard
我們到現在也還是很努力
Look we are now 8:30
你看我們現在8點半了
still doing it here, isn't it?
還在做在這裡 是不是
Taiwan's working hours have been among the longest in the world
台灣的工作時間一直是世界上最長的之一
Out at the top
明列前茅
It seems that South Korea is number one compared to us and is second
好像南韓跟我們比第一 第二
The focus is on the development of backward countries
重點是 落後國家發展之後
Not because, mainly not because their people don't work hard
不是因為 主要不是因為他們人民不努力
You said that China has been
你說中國幾千年來
Did the people not work hard before?
難道以前人民就不努力嗎
So I guess it shouldn't be a main explanatory variable
所以我想它不應該是一個主要解釋變數
I am emphasizing here the role of economic bureaucrats
我在這裡強調經濟官僚的角色
i now go back to the whole noun
我現在回到整個名詞
It is because the economic development of backward countries requires good economic policies
是因為落後國家經濟發展需要好的經濟政策
Because you are behind, you have to catch up
因為你就是落後,你要追趕
You used to be from a traditional agricultural society
你原來是傳統農業社會
What was your original system?
你原來的一套的制度是什麼?
For the imperial examination, you have to write eight-legged essays
科舉,你要寫八股文
then what
然後什麼
For entering an industrial society
對於進入一個工業社會
Of course not well prepared
當然是沒有很好的準備
next to you is facing
你旁邊又面對的是
Very advanced productivity in Europe, America and Japan
非常先進的歐美日的生產力
you have to do
你要做
You certainly need the government to play a very important role
你當然需要政府擔任很重要的角色
So the more backward the role of the government is, the more important it is
所以越落後政府的角色越重要
So it's not that the people don't work hard
所以並不是說人民不努力
It's not that people don't matter
並不是說人民不重要
but you fall behind
而是你越落後
The more you need a focus
你越需要一個集中
collective power
集體的力量
to solve the problem
去解決問題
Japanese Occupation Period
日據時期
Of course the Japanese colonial government
當然日本殖民政府
is a relatively modern
是一個比較現代化
More Advanced Governance Organization
比較先進的治理組織
but
但是
But the Japanese colonial government
但是日本殖民政府
not willing
並沒有這個意願
its will is to develop
它的意志是發展
the economy of their home country
他們的母國的經濟
it has no will
它並沒有意願
no will to develop
也沒有意志要發展
local power
本地的力量
So the Japanese occupation period
所以日據時期
Although the foundation was laid
雖然奠立了基礎
established the system
奠立了制度
But it suppresses the local
但是它壓抑了本地的
economic vitality
經濟的活力
After the environment is suitable
在環境適當了之後
will be able to play
就得以發揮
Just like the coastal areas after China's reform and opening up
就像中國改革開放之後的沿海
Simultaneous Japanese Occupation Period
同時日據時期
limited higher education
高等教育受限
Keep an eye out for talent in an era dominated by America
留意人才在美國主導的時代
Difficult to play
難以發揮
make the contradiction more prominent
使得矛盾更加的凸顯
But in fact
但實際上
Authoritarian repression knows no provinces
威權的鎮壓是不分省級的
Because the asset management committee invests in the mainland
因為資委會在大陸投共
So the resources will be in Taiwan
所以資源會在台灣
Although the role of these people is very important
雖然這些人的角色非常重要
But I believe that you may not have heard of
但是我相信大家可能都沒有聽過
Because as a ministerial unit
因為作為一個部級單位
He voted collectively
他集體投共
The first step of the national government is to kill chickens and enter the marquis
國民政府第一步是殺雞進侯
after they voted
在他們投共之後
Compare Taitang with Taipower
把台湯跟台電的
Dr. Liu MeiGeneral Manager
劉美博士總經理
out of death
出死
Espionage case
匪諜案
After the Chicken Killer enters the Marquis
殺雞的進侯之後
After killing chickens and entering Hou, the capital committee was reorganized
殺雞進侯之後就把資委會改組
But these talents are still necessary
但是這些人才還是必要的
So use it
所以流用
So this becomes a less
因此這個變成一個不太
Frequently Discussed Topics
常討論的議題
Okay, finally let's have some
好 最後我們來處一些
in conclusion
結論
OK, I said it earlier
好 我前面講了
That is to say, backward countries
就是說 落後國家
to develop the economy
要發展經濟
Yes, we can simply say three conditions
有 我們可以簡單講三個條件
the first is
第一就是
external conditions
外在條件
You see, this depends on history
你看 這個就看歷史
historical situation
歷史情況
Sometimes there is no such condition
有的時候就是沒有這個條件
sometimes
有的時候就有
external conditions
外在條件
The second is whether you have this
第二就是你有沒有這個
ability to drive development
推動發展的能力
The third is what I just said
第三就是我剛講的
What I have been emphasizing here is that
我這裡一直強調的就是說
Will to develop
發展的意志
on the ruler
就主政者
cooperating people
配合的人民
Do you have the will to promote development
有沒有推動發展的意志
We can see that
我們可以看到
Just in Taiwan in the early postwar period
就在台灣在戰後初期
There is such a cold war environment
有這樣一個冷戰的環境
that is
就是
America for
美國為了
Under the layout of the cold war
在冷戰的布局下
to contain the middle
為了圍堵中間
The CCP is willing to support the Nationalist Government politically
中共願意在政治上支持國民政府
But give room for development economically
但在經濟上給予發展的空間
So it's certainly an advantage
所以這當然是有利的條件
At the same time, the Japanese colonial government laid a good foundation
同時日本殖民政府奠立了很好的基礎
But the daily role of the Cold War environment
但是冷戰環境每日的角色
Cannot fully explain Taiwan's development achievements
無法完全解釋台灣發展的成績
Very important is a dynamic condition
很重要的是一個能動的條件
On the development of the main capacity and transformation of the new country
就發展新國家的主體能力跟轉型
when we see it we say
我們一看到就是說
Internship in the National Government of the Mainland
在大陸實習國民政府
It is still a relatively backward government
它還是一個比較相對落後的政府
It's... call it light modernization
它的…把它叫做淡現代化吧
It lacks the organizational capacity to effectively rule a vast continent
它缺乏組織能力來有效統治龐大的大陸
Some people joke that its decree does not leave Nanjing
有人說笑話說它政令不出南京城外
that maybe a little more
那 或許可能稍微多一點
After moving to Taiwan, the national government
遷台後 國民政府
Retreat to 10% at the expense of the central government
以中央政府之資撤退到一成
it has accumulated enough talent
它累積了足夠的人才
The experience of failure and the motivation for development
失敗的經驗 以及發展的動力
I think this fits with the foundation left by Japan
我想這個 配合著日本留下的基礎
U.S. assistance made this development possible
美國的協助 使得這個發展得以成功
But what I want to emphasize is that
但我要強調的就是說
The will of the subject's dynamic development is still the key
這個主體的動力發展的意志 仍然是關鍵
Let's look at the Philippines from 1950
我們看看菲律賓從1950年
The income of reinforcements is higher than that of Taiwan to this day
援軍所得高於台灣 到今天
Their financial woes, then I guess it goes without saying.
他們經濟的困境 那我想就不用多說了
I think this is his condition.
我想這個 就是他這方面的條件
very lacking
非常的缺乏
Well, knowing this comparison allows us to understand where we come from
好 認識這個比較可以讓我們理解我們從哪裡來
Then I hope this helps us
然後我希望這樣可以幫助我們
where can we go
我們可以到哪裡去
Good Jingyuan
好 靜元來
In Taiwan's democratization process
在台灣民主化過程中
The transformation of the developmental state has not been entirely successful
發展型國家的轉型並不是完全成功
not totally unsuccessful but not totally successful
不是完全不成功 但是不完全成功
that is
就是
Because once when I was talking about these issues
因為有一次我在講這些問題的時候
someone just said
就有人就說
Yes, democratization has these problems
對 民主化是有這些問題
But are we going back to authoritarian rule?
但難道我們要回到威權統治嗎
What I say is definitely not anti-historical.
我說講這些絕對不是反歷史的說
as if we had a choice
好像我們可以二選一
Press a button again, democratic authority
再按個鈕這樣 民主威權
It means that of course we have to review at any time
而是說我們隨時當然是要檢討
review what we have done
檢討我們做好了什麼
did not do well
沒有做好
Then we will be able to solve our problem shall not
然後我們才能夠解決我們的問題是不是
Then our predicament needs no explanation
然後我們的困局我想不用解釋
Everyone should feel that we are at least economically
大家應該是感覺到我們是至少在經濟上
is in a bind
是處於一個困局
I have said more about this part elsewhere.
這個部分我在別的地方有說的比較多
I'll just say it here
那我這裡就簡單講
Just in the first thirty years it was a
就是在前三十年是一個
economic development in command
經濟發展掛帥
You can see that such a crisis is
你可以看到就是這樣一個危機是
Steady by overcoming fear
藉勝恐懼之下要穩定
but to develop
但是要發展
Of course development is priority
當然發展優先
This dynamic over everything else is very clear
壓過其他一切的這種態勢是非常的清楚
But with the development of society and economic development
但是隨著社會的發展經濟發展
Of course this has to be adjusted
當然這必須調整
But in the process of democratization
但是在民主化過程中
These adjustments were not very successful
這些的調整並不是很成功
A compromise between other social requirements and development goals
社會其他的要求跟發展目標的折衷
We're very partisan right now
我們現在黨派化的非常厲害
so this
所以這個
and the denial of developmentalism
以及對於發展主義的否定
not easy
比較不容易
At least not yet
至少到目前還沒有辦法
create a reasonable
建立一個比較合理的
policy formation model
政策形成模式
Because of the policy we of course have to be a compromise
因為政策我們當然必須是一個折衝
you can't tell me today
你不能說我今天
all nuclear power
所有的核能都不要
then we
那我們
What do you rely on to generate electricity, right?
大家要靠什麼發電對不對
you must
你必須
there is a fold
有一個折衝好
do you have a time table
你是不是有一個time table
are you
你是不是
what price to pay
要付出什麼樣的代價
Are you willing to do it?
大家是不是願意做
do we have a time table
我們是不是有一個time table
you must have a punch
你一定要有個折衝
Economic Development and Environmental Protection
經濟發展跟環保
can only be a fold
只能是一個折衝
Then we must have a society to compare
那我們必須社會有一個比較
develop a more reasonable
發展出一個比較合理
a process acceptable to all
大家可以接受的一個過程
to form such a policy
去形成這樣的政策
But we all know now
但是我們現在大家都知道
One is a more partisan
一個是一個比較黨派對立
Not able to have a rational dialogue
不太能夠有理性對話的狀態
Okay, here's what I'm going to say
好 下面我要講的就是
I originally talked about the problem of the colonial regime
我原來講到這個殖民政權的問題
this is us
就是我們這個
In the mainstream discourse of this society
這個社會主流論述裡面
nativism
其實是一個本土主義
is to be a bit
是要有點
we can say is a
我們可以說是一個
Taiwan's New Nationalism
台灣新國主主義
to build an independent country
要獨立建國
It turned out to be anti-KMT
原來是反國民黨
what about now
那現在呢
Just break the rules and be anti-China
就破章為反中國
this gets in our way
這個就妨礙了我們
to build a
去建立一個
Lack of incentives to drive economic development
缺乏推動經濟發展的動力
difficult to construct
同時難以建構
Viable vision of economic development
巨可行性的經濟發展的願景
at the same time
同時
Now the KMT
現在國民黨
there is no discussion
就沒有論述
There is no way to be sure of your own history
也沒有辦法肯定自己的歷史
no way to position myself
也沒有辦法自我定位
There is no way to find a new motivation
也沒有辦法找到新的動力
I was talking about this
我原來在講這個
It was said during the colonial regime
殖民政權的時候已經說了
that is
就是
i was talking about this
我在講過這些
by
以
Inherited the Chinese nationalism of the old Wang Tucheng
繼承了舊王徒成的中華民族主義
In the process of promoting Taiwan's early economic development
來推動台灣早期經濟發展的過程中
I just explained
我就解釋了
such a nationalism
這樣子的一個民族主義
Let them have a clear vision
讓他們很清楚的有一個願景
That vision is to industrialize Taiwan
那個願景就是要讓台灣工業化
i just said
我剛剛講了
To complete the establishment of Taiwan as soon as possible
使台灣儘速完成建立
The great cause of modern industrial production system
現代工業生產系統的大業
so they have a clear vision
所以他們有一個清楚的願景
This vision goes hand in hand with saying
這個願景就配合著說
We want to foster our own industry
我們要扶植自己的產業
own business
自己的企業
We want to learn from foreign capital
我們要跟外資學習
We have to learn from Europe and the United States
我們要跟歐美學習
but we also need to protect
但是我們也要保護
protection complete
保護完了
Protection is limited
保護有期限
but we are open
但我們開放
but there is a process
但是有一個過程
so you have means and ends
所以你有手段也有目標
Then why do you need protection?
那為什麼需要保護呢
wait a minute because of foreign capital
因為外資等一下
Let me grow up and I will open again
讓我長大了 我再開放
so
這樣
So your democracy has a clear effect
所以你這個民主主義有一個清楚的作用
you are the advanced threat
你就是先進的威脅
wait at the door
在門口等一下
I grow up and I open up again
我長大了 我再開放
So this is the role of economic democracy
所以這個是經濟民主主義的作用
You face advanced foreign forces
你面對外國的先進力量
Then you want to develop your strength
然後你想要發展自己的力量
but
但是
but now
但是現在的
The mainstream discourse that we have developed in the process of democratization
我們在民主化過程中發展出來的主流論述
First with the Kuomintang as the enemy
先是以國民黨為敵人
Said it was a colonial regime, a foreign regime
說是殖民政權 外來政權
So it is an approach to social augmentation
所以它是一個對於社會增化的一個做法
now what i want to say is
現在我要說的是
The economic power of mainland China is not higher than that of Taiwan
國大陸它的經濟力量並不高於台灣
And it has not yet entered Taiwan
然後也還沒有進到台灣
So in an economic sense
所以在經濟意義上
speak up
上來講的話
did not infringe Taiwan's interests
並沒有侵害到台灣的利益
That
那
So one like this
所以這樣子的一個
New nationalism targets anti-China
新國主主義以反中國為目標
There is no way to help us build a
沒有辦法幫助我們去建立一個
A Vision for Future Economic Development
未來經濟發展的願景
ok so i think
好 所以我想
just cut off the past history
就切斷過去的歷史
difficult to understand the past
難以了解過去
don't know how we got here
就不知道我們自己怎麼來的
We must go back to the thread of history
我們必須回到歷史的脈絡
redefine
重新界定
For all the people in Taiwan as one
就台灣所有的人作為一個
economic community
經濟共同體
How do we define our interests
我們怎麼樣去界定我們的利益
Then seek to build a shared vision
然後尋求建立一個共同的願景
the middle
那這個中間
one we have to face
我們必須要面對的一個
the problem is that
問題就是說
How to face in this process
在這個過程中怎麼樣去面對
Taiwan's relationship with mainland China
台灣跟中國大陸的關係
It doesn't matter
沒關係
that part
那這個部分
this part
這個部分
i must say
我必須要說的是
our current thinking
我們目前的想法
The ideas in the mainstream discourse of this society
這個社會主流論述裡面的想法
With Taiwan's early national government
跟台灣早期國民政府的
The pro-American and anti-communist discourses are highly similar to
親美反共的論述是高度的類似
That's what I just said
那這個也就跟我剛才說的
that is to say we
就是說我們
In the course of this discussion
在這個論述過程中
because
因為
the national government
把國民政府
After being a colonial and foreign regime
當作一個殖民跟外來的政權之後
Our role with respect to the United States and Japan
我們對於美國跟日本的角色
There is no way to review positively
沒有辦法正面地去檢討
So our position for ourselves
因此我們對於自己的位置
In fact, there is no way to review it positively.
其實也沒有辦法正面地去檢討
I am
我是
I'm over time
我超過時間
Then I mainly think
那我主要是覺得
if we do these things
我們做這些事情的話
will help us
會幫助我們
start again
再出發
help us go
幫助我們去
It is more reasonable to face cross-strait relations
比較合理的去面對兩岸關係
If we don't face it with this attitude
我們不以這樣態度去面對的話
If you look at history and understand these relationships from history
去看歷史 從歷史中去了解這些關係的話
It's hard for us to find our way
我們也很難去找到我們的出路
ok then i will stop here
好 那我就先說到這裡
Thank you Professor Ji Wang for reinterpreting the development of Taiwan's modeling economy
謝謝吉王教授重新解釋台灣造型經濟的發展
Is there any problem with the rest of the time?
剩下的時間是不是各有什麼問題
We can probably accommodate three or five questions
我們大概也可以容納個三五個問題
come please
來 請
In fact, I think this speech started from the Republic of China
其實我看這個演講就是從民國開始
Here
在這邊
I found from your paper that there are two main axes
我從你的論文裡面發現有兩條主軸
one is national
一條就是國民
Or the Republic of China we are talking about now
或者我們現在講的民國
introduce myself
介紹自我來講
When I talk about the whole context, it sounds like
我講這整個脈絡聽下來就是說
From the Republic of China to Taiwan in 1945
從民國切入台灣1945年
But the final conclusion is that
可是最後的結論是說
Find the bottleneck of development from the history
從歷史中尋找發展的瓶頸
It actually sounds like the bottleneck is still there.
其實聽起來好像那個瓶頸還在
Where is the bottleneck?
瓶頸到底在哪裡呢
That is to say at the end
也就是說最後
You said this KMT KMT
您說這個KMT國民黨
it doesn't affirm itself
它沒有肯定自己
In fact, it has always been very sure of its status
其實它是一直非常肯定自己的地位
That is to say it ignores a thing
也就是說它忽略了一個東西
because it's from 1945 until now
因為它從1945年到現在為止
it does not readjust to a new social situation
它沒有重新調適一個新的社會狀況
Actually it is not without certainty
其實它並不是沒有肯定
100 years since its founding
它建國100年
Including the Republic of China you are using now
包括您現在用的民國
This is all affirmation of itself
這個都是對它自我的肯定
That is, is it not retuned
也就是說它是不是沒有重新調適
Forty years of development
這四十幾年的發展
I'm still going to escape from that old stalk
還是在那個老梗裡面一直去跳脫
It's like saying what you just said
就好比說您剛剛說的
Canan Ogun of this Hatta raincoat
這個八田雨衣的嘉南大郡
that's not a
那不是一個
that's not a term that everyone is familiar with
那不是一個大家都熟悉的名詞
But that is to say, later we slowly discovered from this memory
但就是說後來我們慢慢從這個記憶裡面去發現
Hatta Rain
八田雨
That is naturally related to the so-called Shimen Reservoir
那自然跟這個所謂石門水庫
I think it's a fact that everyone knows
我覺得這是一個大家都知道的事實
The second is to say
第二就是說
talking about
談到的就是說
Does capitalism have to be managed locally?
資本主義是不是要從在地去經營
I think this is a
我覺得這個是一個
For example, for example
譬如說舉個例子來講
Japan has completed from 1895 to 1945
日本在1895年到1945年已經完成了
Three-quarters of Taiwan's so-called railways
台灣四分之三的所謂鐵路
Then KMT probably only played a quarter
那麼KMT可能只玩了四分之一
But he spent 20 or 30 years playing
可是他竟然花了20年或30年去玩
I think
我覺得
Now
現在
Does capitalism follow local management?
資本主義化是不是跟在地經營
ask this so-called
請問這個所謂
A group of elites emerged after the war
戰後來了一批精英
Actually they are
其實他們也是
not on the ground
不是所謂在地
Might be someone from the provinces running this thing
可能是外省人在經營這個東西
so i was thinking
所以我在想說
The things received are not only Taiwan Bank, Taiwan Sugar, and Taiwan Railway
接收的東西不只是台銀、台糖、台鐵
Anyway, many things were operated at that time
反正就是很多東西都是那個時候經營
One question I want to explore is that
我想探討的一個問題就是說
when we are in this understanding
當我們在這個認識裡面
Or split it into two articles
還是把它分成二文來談的話
National Japanese Occupation period
國民日據時期
Also, the identification between us is obvious
還有就是說我們之間的認同很顯然
We are in this serious speech
我們在這場嚴重的這個演講當中
We've got a so-called non-consensus position
我們已經有了一個所謂那個沒有共識的立場了
I'm also talking briefly
我也是簡短講一下
If it's not clear, we'll talk later, thank you
如果不太清楚我們之後再聊謝謝
but i thank you for your opinion
不過我謝謝你的意見
But I don't understand what your problem is
不過我沒有聽懂你的問題是什麼
my question is that
我的問題就是說
modern capitalism
現在話的資本主義
You just said he must be operating locally
您剛說他一定是在地經營的
For example, during the Japanese occupation period, many of his consortiums were from Japanese consortiums.
譬如說日據時期他有很多是日本的財團
right so that no longer does not constitute the so-called
對不對所以那個不再不構成所謂
During the Japanese occupation period, it has entered a modern national system
日據時期已經進入一個現代化的國家體系了
Or it has already entered the capital system. Then, during the Japanese occupation period, there were many American
或者已經進入資本體系那請問在日據時期有很多美國
The situation may be such an example of the Taiwanese operating distance
況可能是台灣人經營的距離這樣的例子
the things you just said at the beginning
就是您剛剛在開頭的時候講的這些東西
I'm starting from here is to say
我是從這個地方開始就是說
Hong Kong is also run by Hong Kong people
香港也是被香港人經營
But he is completely reborn as a Lord of the East
可是他完全是脫胎成為一個東方之主
My point is this
我的觀點是這樣子
I'm good, let me take a look at what you mean
我好我採摩一下你的意思
That is to say, capitalism should not be localized
就是說資本主義是不要在地化的
the answer is yes
答案是是就是
you have to develop
你必須發展出
your own industry your own business
你自己的產業你自己的企業
Hon Hai
譬如說鴻海
He is an industry in Taiwan, and after he developed it, he
他是台灣的產業然後他發展出來了之後他
Other current continents
他現在大陸
employ nearly 800,000 people
有僱用將近80萬人
But his company headquarters and R&D are still located in Taiwan
但是他的公司總部跟研發還是設在台灣
so
所以
So the mainland will still detect it as a Taiwanese company
所以大陸也還是會把它探註是一個台灣的企業
I answered your question like this
我比較這樣回答了你的問題
That is to say, if we the Red Sea
就是說如果我們紅海
If there is no development of the Red Sea
原來沒有發展紅海的話
Waiting for Taiwan, for example, processing and exporting
等臺灣譬如說加工出口
After the foreign capital left
外資走了之後
There are no companies in Taiwan
臺灣就沒有企業了
But we have developed high technology
但是我們有發展高科技
Then although the Red Sea moved a lot of production outside
然後紅海雖然把很多生產外移
but it still leaves a lot
但它還是留下很多
So in Taiwan's high-tech industry
所以就是在臺灣高科技產業
still have a certain size
還是有一定的規模
So I guess this is
所以我想這個就是
It is the localized development of capitalism
就是資本主義在地化發展的
I don't know if this answers your question
我不曉得這樣是不是回答你的問題
ok who else
好 還有哪一位
please
請
ask the professor
請教教授
Our Taiwan technology is in the world
我們臺灣的科技在全世界
is a very important part of the exhibition
是展很重要的份量
Please tell me next time we are in Taiwan
請教你下一個我們臺灣
Can be used internationally like our technology
可以在國際上像我們的科技一樣
what kind of business would it be thank you
企業會是哪一種 謝謝
the answer is not easy
這個答案不是很容易
I have a look
我有看一下
Our development in the last ten years
我們最近十年的發展
that does
那確實
I think it's more worrying
我想比較讓人憂心的
That is to say, for our high-tech
就是說我們對於高科技的
growing since
以來越來越大
For example, the past ten years
譬如說過去十年
If we look at manufacturing
如果我們看製造業的
its distribution ratio
它的分配比例的話
the whole broad
整個廣義的
share of the high-tech industry
高科技業的份額
has reached nearly half
已經達到將近一半
other industries
其他的產業都
Manufacturing is in decline
製造業都在衰退
not that their share
不是就是說他們的份額
Decreasing high-tech industry is increasing
在減少高科技業在增加
never happened before this
在這個之前是從來沒有發生過的
In the past, there were real and some minus
在之前就是有的真有的減
Taiwan is at least
台灣至少還是
Is it a comparison, or a relatively balanced one, one time
是一個比較 還是算比較均衡一點的一個 一個次
an economy but in the last ten years
一個經濟 但是最近十年來
Our dependence on high technology is high to a very high level
我們對於高科技的依賴是高到了一個很高的地步
but if you say it again
但是你話說回來的話
So you said there's not much room for growth
所以你說在成長的空間不大了
i didn't say that
我沒有這樣說
because this means this
因為這個 就是說這個
It is also an opportunity for Taiwan to have such development.
台灣能夠有這樣的發展也是一個
also lucky
也是幸運
That is, because the high-tech industry is a
就是說因為高科技產業是一個
In a growing global
還在不斷成長的全球來講
Because Taiwan can participate in this
那台灣因為能夠參與這個
this whole world
這個全世界
just how to say
就是 怎麼講
it's still going on
就還在不斷
is the frontier of the world
就是全世界的前沿
cutting edge
尖端前沿
He is still pushing forward
他還在不斷地往前推
Then Taiwan can also participate
那台灣還可以參與
Then this piece is constantly expanding
然後這塊是不斷地擴張的
So Taiwan is lucky
所以台灣有這個幸運
able to continue to participate in this
能夠去不斷參與這個
Although it is said that profits continue to become microblogging
雖然說利潤不斷的變得微薄
But this production also has a lot of external shifts
但這個生產也有很多的外移
but
但是
But Taiwan can continue to participate in this industry
但是台灣能夠繼續參與這個產業
It's our grades and luck
是我們的成績跟幸運
Then I think it has a wiki feel
那我是覺得就是維基感要有
but not to say
但也不是說
It is also difficult for us to say that this ratio is too high.
我們也很難說這個比例太高了
won't grow anymore
以後不會成長了
is not what it means
不是這個意思
high tech industry
高科技產業
will continue to grow
還是會繼續成長
that just means
那只是說
we go over this
我們過去這個
The policy approach to combating fear is to say
戒勝恐懼的政策方式就是說
Well, then our twenty years later
好 那我們二十年後的
where are the growth industries
成長產業在哪裡
this batch
就是這一批
This group of old people said they would keep asking such questions
這一批老人說會不斷問這樣的問題
That
那
But this space where the world grows
但是這個世界成長的這個空間
That is, I am not just talking about Taiwan
就是我不是只是講台灣
the whole world
就是整個全球
as far as we mortals can see
我們這些凡人能夠看到的範圍
seems to grow limited
好像成長有限
For example, countries in the world that want to develop
就譬如說全世界想發展的國家
have invested a lot of resources in the biotechnology industry
都投了一大堆資源在生技產業
Just like our Academia Sinica also invested a lot of resources
就像我們中研院也投了很多資源
But the biotech industry
但是生技產業
On the one hand you can say that you also have to vote
你一方面可以說你也不得不投
because of global competition
因為全球競爭
you can't be absent
你也不能缺席
But the biotech industry is a
但是生技產業是一個
impossible to play such an important role
不可能擔任那麼重要的角色
i must say
我必須說
because of his employment
因為他的就業
His employment density is so low
他的就業密度是那麼的低
It is impossible for him to go to the mainland like Hon Hai
就他不可能像鴻海去了大陸
Care for 800,000 people
顧了80萬人
Then go and say it's going to reach a million people
然後去說將要到達到百萬人
Although this means that many of his workers will commit suicide
這雖然說他的工人很多會自殺
but anyway
但是不管怎麼樣
He has provided such a large amount of employment
他是提供了這麼樣大的就業量
The biotech industry is impossible
生技產業是不可能
No matter how it grows, it cannot have such a function
不管再怎麼成長它的型態就不可能有這樣子的功能
So I think for the biotech industry we have to understand
所以我覺得對於生技產業我們必須理解
As if there is no way we can't miss out on global competition
好像全球競爭我們沒有辦法缺席
But we can't be based on such a big backward look
但是我們不可能基於那麼大的後望
Because of its employment volume, the value it generates is limited
因為它的就業量 它所產生的價值都有限
and is assuming that you can develop
並且是假設你可以發展
Then there is another one in Taiwan. Is there one that can be said?
那台灣還有下一個有沒有一個可以就是說
Comparable to yours with this technology
跟這個科技可以同比你的那個
The kind of business that can grow again
可以再次發展的那一種企業
I don't think we are quite
我覺得我們不太 怎麼說
we can't say
我們沒有辦法說
but i think there are some
但是我覺得有一些
as far as Taiwan
就台灣
But there are industries that have the ability to follow
但是有產業是有這種能力去跟隨
For example, what is possible
譬如說什麼樣的有可能
What future industry is the United States developing?
有什麼美國在發展什麼未來的產業
Taiwan has the opportunity to participate and follow up
台灣是可以有機會去參與去跟進
I think this part is that we can actually have this ability
這個部分我覺得其實是我們是可以有這個能力
But I think our biggest challenge is
但是我覺得我們最大的挑戰是
Can we be more active in business
我們可不可以更積極的去經營
Use the mainland market with the mainland
跟大陸的利用大陸的市場
What kind of cooperative development should we do at a relatively high level?
去以比較高的層次去做什麼樣的合作發展
For example, Taiwan's high-tech manufacturers have their status
譬如說台灣的高科技廠商是有它的地位
Although the mainland government is very courageous
大陸這個政府雖然非常有魄力
But with its courage, there is no way to support high-tech members
但是以它的魄力沒有辦法扶植出高科技成員
Of course you can see that there are all kinds of possibilities
這個中間你當然可以看到說好像有各種可能
So far, Taiwanese businessmen have gone to the mainland alone
到目前為止台商去大陸都是單打獨鬥
able to develop very limited
能夠發展得非常有限
But fields like this
但是像這種領域
we see some possibilities
我們就看到一些可能性
But this must be a high level of difficulty
但這個必須要就是高難度的高層的
What kind of binocular strategy will be developed by the senior level with social support
有社會支持的高層的去發展出什麼樣的雙眼的策略
thank you teacher
謝謝教師
That one is my personal forward advice
那個其中是我個人的前進請教
what we just talked about
我們剛才談到的
Taiwan's 60-person economy
台灣這個60人的經濟
Of course, the Kuomintang has a lot of technical officials.
當然是國民黨量很多技術官的
and very talented
而且很有才幹
But Taiwan's CNC is simply
但是台灣的CNC的簡直
I think it provides a lot of motivation
我想是提供了很大的動力
The one who came out of the mountain in 1948 was the 37th year of Mongolia
四八年出山的就是蒙古三十七年
So from this world in the process of my study
所以從這個世界上在我讀書的過程當中
After an official full from us tell us what the 375 checkout is
從我們一個官方的完整之後告訴我們什麼是三七五檢出
And the Kuomintang beautifies the tigers very much
而且國民黨把山君的都非常的美化
I heard Wen Mao Mao is the landlord
我聽文貓貓那邊是地主
My dad is a mother
我爸爸那邊是人母
So the mother may benefit as well.
所以人母這邊可能也得到好處
But the landlord is God's beloved
但是地主是神愛的
Mother
人母嘛
So when the Kuomintang detected 375
所以國民黨當初在三七五檢出的時候
He said this private land
他說這個私人土地
In less than a year, he immediately included four Taiwan dollars in a box
不到一年馬上就把他台幣四大含一框
So Yuan Guo said what he said is the history of our past dynasties.
所以原國講他這個所謂就是我們過去歷代的歷史
Centralize the country's resources to redistribute
把國家的資源集中要重新分配
But I've concentrated a lot of motivation during this time
但是我這段時間就集中很大的動力
But from our official 375 checkout beautification
但是從來我們的官方的三七五檢出美化
I have visited Ma Guoshidu Taiwan several times for examination materials.
拜訪馬國師都台灣考材好幾次啊
Come to the country, the Democratic Party can do it when they go back
對國家都來,民主黨回去能做到
In addition, for this three-dimensional, if you can do a kind of data research on it
另外這個立體,假如你能夠把他做一種數據上的研究
What kind of benefits does this provide to Taiwan, and what kind of cloth number does it offset?
到底這個是對台灣提供什麼好處,抵消什麼樣的佈號
So becoming Taiwan is until now every election, I still regard this as a hype topic
所以變成台灣是到現在每一次選舉對我還把這個當作是個炒作的話題
It is also the differences in the policy consciousness of the people in the north and south of Taiwan
也是台灣南北部的人民這個政策意識上的分歧
So I think we should have the manpower to study him and announce this
所以覺得我們應該是有人力去把他研究一下,把他公布這個
Because I think he made the boar view too glorified
因為我覺得他把這個山豬檢視太美化了
Because I want to get first-hand information about this influence from the public security side, from the public security side.
因為我要從公安那邊,公安那邊拿到都是第一手的民間的這個影響的信息
That's a big gap with Gongying's information.
那跟公英的信息差距很大
And Dongying's information is very vague
而東英的信息很模糊
Just like Ou Ba, Hideo has never been sad
就跟歐巴士中英朗從來都沒有沒難過
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you, I think this land reform depends on whether you want to ask the landlord or the electric farmer
謝謝,我想這個土地改革如果看你是要問地主還是問電農
the answer will be very good
得到的答案會非常好
both sides for me
對我兩邊都有
Is the answer different?
答案是不是不一樣呢
I'm not saying now that I'm going to hold him accountable
我現在不是說要追究他這個豪壞
Are you announcing this fact?
是把這個事實公布嘛
because of his
因為他那個
well i can only answer briefly
好我只能簡單回答
My first answer is that I think
我第一個就回答就是我想
because that is a very clear
因為那個是一個很清楚的
how to say clearly
很清楚的怎麼說
Violation of private property rights
違反私有財產權
go with the power of the country
以國家的力量去
move to private property rights
去動到私有財產權
The first is to pick up rent
第一個是撿租
The second is to expropriate land
第二個是徵收土地
and then distributed to electric farmers
然後發放給電農
so i thought
那所以我想
Of course he violated the interests of the landlord
他當然侵害到地主的利益
right
對
So it's a strange thing that a landowner would approve of that.
所以地主會贊成那是很奇怪的事情
So the landlords borrow Taiwan dollars when they come
所以地主腦來就借台幣
Electric farmers pay different regulatory NT dollars
電農交入分歧的管制新台幣
cut this picture back
剪這項圖回來
no no no
沒有沒有沒有
At that time, the three-seven-five cutting beads were changing
三七五剪珠那個時候正是在換
The first phase of Sanqiwu Jianzhu was in 1949
三七五剪珠第一期是1949
was changing at that time
那個時候正在換
In terms of Taiwan dollars New Taiwan dollars
就台幣新台幣
He is 11 months less than a year
他11個月不到一年
It seems that in less than a year, there will be no NT dollars
好像不到一年就要不要新台幣
New Taiwan dollar same year
新台幣同一年
1949 Two Things Doing Together
1949年兩件事情一起做
From the first phase to 1949, the first phase to making three seven five cut beads
第一期到1949第一期到做三七五剪珠
then in summer
然後夏天的時候
I forgot which month
我忘了哪一月的時候
seems like november
好像就11月
Is there still something like that Linma in it?
像那個林馬裡面還有嗎
This NTD is in the Danhua rules
這個新台幣時是淡華規則裡面
well, the details we can't talk about here
好那細節我們沒有辦法在這裡談
but i think that is
但是我想那個是
Let me tell you about his effect
我講一下他的效果的話
His very important effect is
他很重要的效果就是
He forced an end to landownership by coercive force
他強制以強制的力量結束了地主經濟
Because landlord economy means
因為地主經濟的意思就是說
social elite
社會的精英
not saying good or bad
不是說好壞
Because China has been like this for thousands of years
因為過去中國幾千年就是這樣子
That is, it is a traditional landlord economy
就是那個是一個傳統的地主經濟
This is the landlord world
就是這個地主間 世生間
This official is your imperial examination to become an official
這個官 就是你科舉去做官
This is a Chinese system
這是一個中國的體制
but you i just said
但是你 我剛講
It's CO's bourgeois revolution
就是CO的資產階級革命
It just took hundreds of years
就是花了幾百年的時間
The feudal is the feudal aristocracy
把這個封建的 就是封建貴族
and this land of the Church
以及教會的這個土地
and the privilege exited
以及特權退出了
Then began a capitalist economy
然後開始了一個資本主義的經濟
the land reform
這個土地改革
It is also a top-down
也是一種由上而下進行的這種
bourgeois revolution
資產階級的革命
so it ended the landlord economy
所以它結束了地主經濟
It means that the elites of society can no longer rely on
就是社會的精英不能夠再靠
This landlord is very good
就這個地主很好
I'll go, I'll buy land if I have money
我就去 有了錢我就去買土地
then landowner
然後收地主
as a means of livelihood for the elite of this society
來作為這個社會精英的謀生之道
This is the past landlord
這個是過去地主
the past economy
就是過去經濟
Our traditional agricultural economy
我們傳統農業經濟
The Economy of China's Agricultural Society
中國農業社會的經濟
the existing model
的既有模式
we can't say
我們不能夠說
he must
他一定
call it morally bad
就把它說成是道德上的不好
i think it's historical
我想這就是歷史的
glasses of history
歷史的眼鏡
but you are under pressure from the west
但是你在西方的壓力下
you
你
Everybody thinks we have to industrialize
大家都覺得我們必須要工業化
we have to get into a
我們必須要進入一個
this different era
這個不同的時代
that this
那這個
What the national government did
這個國民政府做的
the land reform
這個土地改革
has an effect
有一個效果
Regardless of the process will definitely
不管過程裡一定會
Will
一定會
The interests of the landlord must be damaged
就地主的利益一定受到損害
big small
大的小的
Of course there are varying degrees
當然有不同程度的
must be damaged
一定受到損害
But Diannong
但電農
Of course some electric farmers benefit
有些電農當然是得利
that this
那這個
but more importantly
但是更重要的是
it is an era
它是一個化時代的
changes in the times
化時代的變化
It forces the economy of Taiwan into a different era
它強迫台灣這個經濟進入一個不同的時代
At the same time, the national government is also under greater pressure
同時國民政府也有更大的壓力
Because the elite of your society can no longer live as landlords
因為你的社會的精英不能再做地主為生了
you have to give them a way out
你必須要給他們一個出路
you must industrialize
你一定要進行工業化
You must develop industry and commerce
你一定要去發展工商業
and let these people have a way out
然後讓這些人有出路
So this is the meaning of his words age
所以這是他的話時代的意義
In this process, of course, there are gains and losses.
在這個過程中當然有人有得有失
no more questions
不想還沒有別的問題
Thanks
謝謝
Hello Professor, I have two questions
教授您好 請問兩個問題
The first one is the Taiwan Miracle mentioned at the beginning
第一個是一開頭的時候提到台灣奇蹟
including political miracles and economic miracles
包括政治的奇蹟跟經濟的奇蹟
That kind of statement is Taiwan's economic development
那一種說法是台灣的經濟發展
democratization of politics with facilitation
有促進的政治的民主化
May I ask if such a statement is established?
請問這樣的說法是成立
Can it be established?
可以成立的嗎
This is the first question
這是第一個問題
The second question is mentioned in the introduction
第二問題是在簡介有提到說
professor you are right now
教授您現在對
That is, the situation after the reform and opening up in contemporary China has been studied
就是當代中國改革開放之後的狀況有研究
Assuming this statement is true
假設這樣說法是成立的話
Can we have such optimistic expectations for contemporary China?
我們可以對當代中國有這樣的比較樂觀的期待嗎
because of economic development
因為經濟的發展
So will politics be more democratic or something like that?
所以政治會不會比較民主之類的
this is the second question
這是第二個問題
Thanks
謝謝
ok very important question
好 很重要的問題
I think all backward countries
我覺得所有的落後國家
when he started
他在開始的時候
His politics must be rights protection
他的政治一定是維權的
is that it should be a common phenomenon
就是那應該是一個普遍的現象
there is no reason
就沒有什麼任何理由
he is not an activist
他不是維權的
that economic development
那經濟發展
He will surely educate many
他一定會讓很多人得到教育
Get a lot of independent economic resources
得到很多獨立的經濟資源
Then the economy develops better
然後經濟發展越好
The more individuals with independent economic resources
這些有獨立經濟資源的個人越多
Everyone's education level has improved
大家這個教育程度提高
improved living standards
生活水準提高
So the economy grows
所以經濟越發展
they want to get involved in politics
他們要參與政治
the right to participate in politics
要取得參與政治的權利的
desire will be higher
的願望會越高
So the better your economy develops
所以你經濟發展越好
It is the desire of some people and the existing political
它是一些人的願望跟既有的政治
The higher the tension in the rights-defending political system will be
維權政治體系的緊張程度會越高
so
所以
but
但是
but what happens between
但是這之間會發生什麼樣
That is to say it is not a necessity
就是說它不是一個必然
What I just said is inevitable
就是我剛剛講的是必然
That is to say, the tension between
就是說這個之間的緊張程度
pressure on the existing political system
對於既有政治的體制的壓力
The pressure to change will be stronger
要改變的壓力會越強
but
但是
But there is no necessity in this
但是這個裡面沒有必然
say it will
說一定會
what must happen
一定會發生什麼樣子
for example
譬如說
Taiwan and South Korea are relatively successful examples
台灣跟南韓都是比較成功的例子
That
那
For example, we see that Thailand A does not seem to be so
譬如說我們看泰國A好像沒有那麼
relatively less successful
相對來講沒有那麼成功
that we can
就是我們可以
But Taiwan and South Korea
但台灣跟南韓
also have different paths
也各自有不同的道路
right
對不對
so i guess there is something inevitable
所以我想有什麼必然的話
I just think what I just said is a kind of necessity
就是我覺得我剛剛講的是一種必然
economic development
就是經濟發展
The better it is, the greater the pressure on the existing authoritarian system
越好它對於既有威權體制的壓力越大
But how will this road go
但是這個路會怎麼走
Depends on the existing conditions in each place
就看各個地方的既有的條件
So it's hard to say it's going to be one way or the other
所以很難講說一定會這樣或那樣
But we can say that the more average your original development
但我們可以說你原來發展的越平均
more evenly distributed income
所得分配越平均
Then the allocation of resources is more fair
然後資源分配的比較公正
This democratization process should be better
這個民主化的過程應該會比較好
but I think there are many different factors
但是我想這裡面有很多不同的因素
For example, if you spend two minutes talking
譬如說如果花兩分鐘講
That is to say Taiwan
就是說台灣的話
We have taken a more convenient path
我們是走了一個比較便捷的道路
we can just say yes
我們就是可以說是
a subject-based
以審激為主的一個本主化的
agree with the political path
就認同政治道路
This is also because the national government, in its authoritarian way,
這也是因為國民政府以他威權的方式
I just said
就我剛剛講了
The development of the economy in this military way
這個軍賦方式的發展經濟
So the issue of that distribution is in Taiwan
所以那種分配的議題在台灣
hard to be a dominant
很難成為一個主導性的
to mobilize the people
的去鼓動民眾
This income distribution is too unfair
這個所得分配太不公平了
or how
或怎麼樣
this kind of issue
這種議題
Assigned issues because
分配的議題因為
under authoritarian rule
威權統治下
He has more or less dealt with
他都多多少少有一些處理
Therefore the issues of these assignments
因此這些分配的議題
not easily provoked
不太容易激起
to rally these forces of democratic opposition
去聚集這些民主反對的力量
But the politics of identity
但是這個認同的政治
It's easy to distinguish you from me
就很容易區分你跟我
is an easier path
就是是一個比較容易的道路
So Taiwan has taken such a path
所以台灣就走了這樣的一個道路
has its benefits
有它的好處
has its downsides
有它的壞處
south korean words
南韓的話
He's a very solid mobilizer
他就是非常紮實的動員
it's him
就是他
His most critical is 1987
他最關鍵的是1987
millions of students
幾百萬學生
union what church
工會什麼教會
Going to the street to have a bloody confrontation with the military and police
上街跟軍警搭身了血腥的衝突
that is a decisive
那那個是一個決定性
Then they were in the post-war student movement
那他們在戰後學生運動
they have very guild sports
他們有非常公會運動
has his long-term foundation
有他長遠的基礎
so you meet boy friends
所以你碰到男孩的朋友
they are very proud
他們都非常驕傲
their civil society is very powerful
他們的市民社會是非常有實力的
For example, like I met a friend
譬如說像我碰到一個朋友
He has a real NGO
他有一個那個才是真的NGO
They are supported by membership associations
他們是靠會員的會會來支持
Then there are 100 dedicated staff
然後有100個專職人員
So-called NGOs in Taiwan
台灣的所謂的NGO
I also know that there are full-time professionals with more than 100
那些我也知道有專職有超過100的
But they all rely on the government's position to report
但都是靠政府的職務外報
we don't have that strength
我們沒有這種實力
our so-called civil society
我們的所謂的市民社會
no such basis
沒有這樣的基礎
but the boy has
但男孩有
that's different
那這是不一樣的
so
所以
but they paid a high price
但他們付出很大的代價
like i agree
像我認同
He said that your apartment is on the street
他就說你們這個公寓上街
or what rights take to the streets
或者什麼權益上街
Then I went back home for dinner
然後也就全身還是退回家吃飯
He said we went to the streets when we were young
他說我們年輕時候上街
It's just that everyone's head is bleeding
就是大家都是頭破血流
Go back to dorms
回到宿舍
if you can go back
如果回得去的話
So they pay different prices
所以他們付出的代價不一樣
that's what you paid for
那你付出了這樣的代價
the foundation of your civil society
那你的這個公民社會的基礎
it might be different
可能就會是不一樣
so i feel all the things
所以我覺得所有的事情
all have something to say
都是有話有話
So Taiwan South Korea
所以台灣 南韓
we are very very
我們非常非常
country of brothers
兄弟之邦
postwar development of all
一切的戰後的發展
very very similar
非常非常高度相似
But we see this democratic path
但我們看到這個民主道路
not exactly the same
不完全一樣
Mainland China really dare not say
中國大陸真的不敢說
But I think that structure
但是我覺得那個結構
we have now seen
我們現在已經看到了
His developmental anger is very good
他的發展生氣非常好
very stressful
壓力非常大
with the existing system
跟既有制度的
But China is really big
但中國真的太大了
I can't go on anymore
我下面就說不下去了
our time is up
我們時間到了
We thank Professor Ju Wangwen with applause
我們以掌聲謝謝橘王文教授
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you for half a year
謝謝他各位半年